<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The cabinet of the Jesuits secrets opened in which there are many things relating to the church and clergy of England : as also the ways by which they encrease the number and wealth of their society on the ruines of kingdoms and families : in part began by Dr. Oats from an Italian copy, but now more largely discovered from a French copy printed at Colon, 1678 / made English by a person of quality.</title>
            <title>Monita Secreta Societatis Jesu. English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 122 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A31633</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C189</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18321</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12111244</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12111244</idno>
            <idno type="VID">54204</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A31633)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 54204)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 57:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The cabinet of the Jesuits secrets opened in which there are many things relating to the church and clergy of England : as also the ways by which they encrease the number and wealth of their society on the ruines of kingdoms and families : in part began by Dr. Oats from an Italian copy, but now more largely discovered from a French copy printed at Colon, 1678 / made English by a person of quality.</title>
                  <title>Monita Secreta Societatis Jesu. English.</title>
                  <author>Person of quality.</author>
                  <author>Zahorowski, Hieronim.</author>
                  <author>Oates, Titus, 1649-1705.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 44 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Jonathan Robinson and George Wells ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of two articles from Le cabinet jesuitique (p. 1-90): Les secrets des jesuites, and Advis secrets de la Societé de Jesus.</note>
                  <note>Principal authorship of the Monita secreta societatis Jesu attributed to Hieronim Zahorowski.  Cf. Reusch, C. Index der verbotenen Bücher, 1885, v. 2, p. 280-281 ; Encyklopedyja Powszechna.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesuits --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:54204:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:54204:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>THE CABINET OF THE Jeſuits Secrets OPENED. In which there are many things relating to the Church and Clergy of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As alſo the ways by which they encreaſe the Number and Wealth of their <hi>Society,</hi> on the ruines of King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms and Families.</p>
                  <p>In part began by Dr. <hi>Oats</hi> from an <hi>Italian</hi> Copy; But now more largely diſcovered, from a <hi>French</hi> Copy, printed at <hi>Colon,</hi> 1678.</p>
                  <p>Made <hi>Engliſh By a Perſon of Quality.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Licenſed, <hi>Feb.</hi> 14. 1678/9.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Jonathan Robinſon,</hi> and <hi>George Wells,</hi> in St. <hi>Paul's</hi> Church-yard. 1679.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:54204:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:54204:2"/>
                  <head>To the READER.</head>
                  <p>THeſe Papers were not originally intended for the Preſs, but for the uſe of an intimate Friend, and had poſſibly never gone further, if they who are the ſubject Matter of them, had not made it neceſſary to give my dear Country-Men this inſight into their deſigns upon us, and the methods by which they hope to attain their ends upon us.</p>
                  <p>There is ſcarce any ſort of Perſons in the Nation, to whom the knowledg of theſe things may not be uſeful, the Recuſants themſelves not excepted; and it is moſt certain the Book was firſt printed by, and for ſuch.</p>
                  <p>But then it is moſt neceſſary for the Country-Gentry, and for them I chiefly deſign it, that they may be no longer cheated by the fair Carriage and inſinuating Behavior of theſe Men, and their Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples. They are ſaid to be good Company and civil Men, and which is more, that they ſeldom ſpoil the Mirth and Pleaſure of the reſt of the Company with Diſputations, but rather make themſelves agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able with Stories and News. But for all that, theſe Men have a deſign, if not upon your Lives and Perſons, yet upon your Families and Eſtates, and you ſhall one day pay dearly for their Acquaintance, or elſe they will miſs what they moſt intend.</p>
                  <p>They rarely ſeek the Acquaintance of any but Perſons of great Eſtate, and of ſuch as have ſame Authority in their Countrey, and theſe they flatter and careſs with all the little Arts of indearments imaginable; but eſpecially if they find them ignorant of the World, and not too much verſt in, or fixt to the eſtabliſhed Religion: for with theſe they care not to aſſociate: Except it be in order to ſeduce their Children, and herein they often prevail by matching their Daughters to them; for they will not willingly marry a Son to a Proteſtant Woman. And the ſtopping this Gap, which hath ſeduced many great Families, is a work as well worthy the thoughts of the Parliament as any other whatever.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:54204:3"/>
But the uſe they make of Perſons in Authority is yet more pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: by their power they awe and curbe the inferior People that they durſt not offend them, and the late Plot had never come ſo near its execution, had it not been for this. For their preparation of Arms was clearly enough diſcovered, to have put us upon our guard, but that they uſed the Authority of ſome Juſtices of the Peace to puniſh thoſe People, who had ſeen and obſerved them, and had alſo courage enough to report their Knowledg. By this means alſo they baffle the execution of all Laws againſt them; and doubtleſs in private deride and ſcorn thoſe, whom they thus cajole in publick.</p>
                  <p>And here let not the Diſſenters flatter themſelves, as if they of all others had leaſt converſation with them. Their new virtue of <hi>Toleration</hi> hath done theſe Men more ſervice than is thought of. And <hi>Coleman</hi> was no Fool when he told the <hi>French</hi> King's Confeſſor, That if they could once obtain an Act of Parliament, for a general Liberty of Conſcience, They ſhould afterwards do in effect what they liſt; and a little after in the ſame Letter, <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>The Trial of</hi> Edward Coleman, <hi>page</hi> 54:</note> That this would give the greateſt blow to the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion here that ever it received ſince its Birth. They may ſee by this who are to reap the benefit of their Labours for a Toleration. And Mr. <hi>Oats</hi> would infinitely oblige the World, if he would publiſh an account of the Cheats of this ſort, he hath ſeen practiſed amongſt them.</p>
                  <p>As for the Tranſlation I ſhall ſay but this; it is faithfully done, and I have uſed as much as I could poſſibly, the very words of the Original. And now if God may have Glory, and the Church and Nation Service by it; I ſhall never wiſh for more.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>Farewel.</salute>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:54204:3"/>
                  <head>THE SECRETS OF THE JESUITS.</head>
                  <p>THE Laws and Conſtitutions upon which the <note n="*" place="margin">Order. <hi>This Author uſeth; words indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently,</hi> viz. <hi>the</hi> Religion, Order <hi>and</hi> Company <hi>of the</hi> Jeſuits <hi>which they call the Society themſelves.</hi>
                     </note> Religion of the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits was eſtabliſhed, make it ſo clearly appear that it was by the Inſpiration of the Holy Ghoſt that <hi>Ignatius</hi> planted it in the Vineyard of the Lord that no Man can juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doubt thereof. For whoever had conſidered it, in its firſt riſe, would have had great reaſon to hope that it was the Tree that ſhould produce the Antidote againſt the venom of <hi>Hereſies,</hi> and that it ſhould ſend forth thoſe bloſſoms of Chriſtian and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Works, which being once ſcented by Sinners, ſhould compel them to abandon the ſtench of Sin, and follow the odour of Repentance. And truly ſo long as thoſe good Fathers, from whom it deriv'd its Birth, bedew'd it with their Charity; and that it was cultivated according to their Intentions, it is certain the Fruits which aroſe of it, were fair and large to a Wonder, as well in relation to the excellent education of Children, as the Converſion of Souls, and the propagation of the true Faith of the Catholick Religion. But the Devil, who imploys as much ſubtilty in the deſtruction of the works and deſigns of God, as good men do labour to advance them, took occaſion even from the Grandeur of this Religion, and the marvelous progreſs it made in a ſhort time, to pervert the end of its Inſtitution: for by a ſubtile Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, inſtead of the firſt branches of Charity, which are now almoſt quite
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:54204:4"/>
withered, he hath ingrafted the two moſt pernicious Affections in the World <hi>Ambition</hi> and <hi>Avarice;</hi> which cauſe ſo great a miſchief to Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, that it is ſcarce poſſible to imagine a greater; as I hope I ſhall demonſtrate in this diſcourſe. In the entry of which I proteſt before God, that it is neither Intereſt nor Paſſion moves my Pen, but ſimply the zeal of the publick Good; to the Advantage of which I believe my ſelf obliged to uſe my utmoſt endeavours; hoping that their Diſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations and Arts being once known by Princes, there ſhall in time be a remedy provided.</p>
                  <p>Now the firſt thing which ſhould be conſidered is, that the Religion of the Jeſuits being ſolely provided for the education of Children, of which there is neither Kingdom nor City which ſtands not in need, it was at firſt deſired on all hands, and favoured by moſt Princes, ſo that it made a greater progreſs in a few years, than moſt others have done in many Ages. But this greatneſs which for the moſt part introduceth a change of Manners, kindled in theſe Children of <hi>Ignatius</hi> ſo great a Love to their Society; that perſuading themſelves, it was of greater uſe to the Church of God then all the reſt, and better fitted for the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the World, they concluded amongſt themſelves that they ought to imploy all their care and craft in the enlarging of it; becauſe with it they augmented the Militia of Jeſus Chriſt, the good of the whole Church, and the antient Patrimony of our Lord, if I may thus ſpeak their Language.</p>
                  <p>And here it is that I ſhall need the Subtilty of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> and the Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of <hi>Tully,</hi> to unfold the ſtrange manner which theſe Fathers uſe in a conſtant increaſe of their Society, which perhaps will ſeem impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to many by reaſon of its Novelty; but it will be ſufficient for me to remark ſome few things only, leaving a ſpacious Field for every one to form ſuch an <hi>Idea</hi> of it, as ſhall appear moſt reaſonable to him; and to this purpoſe I will content my ſelf with the propoſing ſome Heads or Points rather, which may ſerve my deſign of affording a certain Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation to the Reflections and Diſcourſes of thoſe, who will exerciſe themſelves in the Contemplation of this Subject.</p>
                  <div n="1" type="part">
                     <head>I.</head>
                     <p>The Jeſuites foreſaw, they could never raiſe their Society to that heighth of Grandeur they aſpired to, by doing nothing but Teach, Preach and Adminiſter the Sacraments, or by the ſole performance of other ſuch like Religious Offices. For although at firſt they were enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd by many with a very great affection, as I have ſaid before; yet at length they perceived, that time diminiſhed this Love, which made them ſuſpect their Religion had made its greateſt efforts in its infancy;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:54204:4"/>
and therefore they were put to the neceſſity of inventing two other means to aggrandiſe it, the firſt of which was to diſcredit with Princes, and in conſequence with all others they could, all the other Orders, pretending great imperfections in them. So that by this malicious ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs, having raiſed their own greatneſs upon the ruine of others, they poſſeſt themſelves of a great number of Monaſteries, and Abbies, and other great Revenues, by their Slanders diſpoſſeſſing the former Own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. The ſecond was by inſinuating themſelves into the Affairs of State, ingaging in their Intereſt the greateſt part of the Chriſtian Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, in ſuch a ſubtile and artificious manner, that as it is difficult to penetrate, ſo it is almoſt impoſſible to explain it perfectly. Their <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral,</hi> to whom all the reſt pay a very exact Obedience, recides continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally at <hi>Rome;</hi> he hath made choice of ſome Fathers, who becauſe they are alway with him, are called <hi>Aſſiſtants,</hi> and there is at leaſt one of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Nation, from which they take their Name, one calling himſelf the Aſſiſtant of <hi>France,</hi> the other of <hi>Spain,</hi> the third of <hi>Italy,</hi> the fourth of <hi>England,</hi> the fifth of <hi>Auſtrich;</hi> and ſo of all the other Provinces and Kingdoms. The duty of each Aſſiſtant is to give advice to the General of all thoſe events of State which paſs in the Kingdom or Province he repreſents; which he is inabled to do by means of the correſpondence he holds there, who making their abode in the chief Town of that Kingdom or Province, inform themſelves carefully of the State, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Inclination and Intentions of Princes, with which in concluſion they advertiſe the Aſſiſtants every Poſt, giving them advice of what hath been diſcovered, or what hath lately happened, ſo that all theſe Pac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quets arriving at <hi>Rome,</hi> the <hi>General</hi> calls to his Counſel all his Aſſiſtants, who preſent him as it were with an Anatomy of the World; telling him the Intereſts and Deſigns of all the Chriſtian Princes. After which, having conſidered all thoſe things were written to them, and having examined and compar'd them one with another, at length they raiſe the Concluſion, which is, that they ought to favour the affairs of one Prince, and hinder thoſe of another, according to their own Intereſt and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit. So that as Spectators ſee the blots better than the Gameſters, ſo theſe Fathers having in view the Intereſts of all the Princes, apply with the greater facility, the neceſſary means to improve the affairs of him that is moſt deſpoſed to their Intereſt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="part">
                     <head>II.</head>
                     <p>The ſecond Point which deſerves to be chiefly conſidered after this, is, That it is extreamly miſchievous, that Religious Perſons ſhould meddle with State Affairs, their duty obliging them to attend wholly the Salvation of their own Souls, and thoſe of their Neighbours. So
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:54204:5"/>
that the Jeſuits intrieguing in the Civil Government, more than the very Seculars themſelves, it is abſolutely neceſſary, for the avoiding many moſt dangerous Conſequences, to provide ſome remedy againſt ſo great a diſorder. For, in the firſt place, the Jeſuits take the Auricular Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of a great part of the Nobility of the Catholic States; ſo that to get leiſure for this, they will no longer admit the Poor into their <note n="*" place="margin">Theſe are certain private places in Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, made for that purpoſe, like our Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-Desks, with Pewes on either ſide, of the ſame height.</note> 
                        <hi>Confeſſionals,</hi> and very often they are the Confeſſors of Princes too: So that by this means it is eaſy to penetrate into all their Deſigns, and learn all the reſolutions, as well of the Princes as of their Subjects, of which they preſently give advice to their <hi>General,</hi> or to the <hi>Aſſiſtants</hi> which remain at <hi>Rome.</hi> Now any Man that hath the leaſt Judgment, may perceive the damage which this ſort of People bring to Soveraign Princes, who have no other end in any thing but their own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt; for all the World knows that there is ſcarce any thing more ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary than Secreſy for the Preſervation of States; ſo that if this thing be once loſt, they ordinarily fall to ruine; which without doubt is the reaſon why all wiſe Princes are ſo careful to preſerve it, and keep their Intentions from being known; whereas on the other ſide, having often obſerved that they become the wiſer by the knowledg of the deſigns of others, and that thereby they govern their own Affairs the better, they endeavour by all ways to attain the knowledg of them, entertaining for that purpoſe Ambaſſadors and Spies with conſiderable expences, though for the moſt part without a conſiderable advantage, becauſe the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports which are made by their <note n="†" place="margin">Miniſters.</note> Ambaſſadors, are for the moſt part not very faithful. But I can aſſure any Man, that the <hi>General</hi> of the Jeſuites, and his Aſſiſtants, have this advantage, that they are truly and very particularly inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of what ever paſſeth in the moſt ſecret Conſultations; both by means of Confeſſions, and of the Inquiries which their Correſpondents make, who live in all the chief places of Chriſtendom, and alſo by the aid of their other Adherents, which I will ſpeak of hereafter: So that they do better underſtand, as I may ſay, what are the Forces, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues, the Expences, and Deſigns of Princes, than the Princes themſelves. And all this without any other expence than the charge of Letters, which in truth amounts to a conſiderable Charge, ſeeing that every Poſt, according to the account of the Poſt-maſters, they come to 60, 70, 80, and ſometimes 100 Crowns of Gold a Return. By which it is eaſy to conjecture, that having ſo exact a knowledg of the Intereſts of Princes, it is equally in their power to diminiſh their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:54204:5"/>
with other Princes, to make them loſe their Authority with their Subjects, to raiſe them up what Enemies they pleaſe: and laſtly, to raiſe up their own Subjects againſt them, with ſo much the greater facility, that by means of Confeſſions, and of their Emiſſaries, they pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrate to the bottom of the Souls of their Vaſſals, and ſo diſcover all thoſe that are well or ill affected. So that by the reports which are made them of the affairs of State, they may without difficulty ſow the Seeds of Enmity amongſt Princes, and involve them in a thouſand ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picions; And alſo of the knowledg which they have of the Minds of their Subjects, it is no leſs eaſy for them to foment in them Contempt of their Governours, and give birth to all ſorts of troubles and ſeditions. From all this any Man muſt conclude, that Intereſt of State will never permit any Prince to chooſe for his Confeſſors theſe ſorts of Men, who apply themſelves with ſo much care to pry into the Affairs of State; and which make uſe of the knowledg they have thus gotten, as the moſt effectual means of inſinuating themſelves into the favour of other Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentates. And they ought much leſs to ſuffer their Counſellors, their Principal Miniſters, and their houſhold Officers, to take them for their Confeſſors, eſpecially, becauſe we live in an age abundantly furniſhed with Perſons, who are not inferiour to the Jeſuites neither in Knowledg, nor in Vertue, and are as able to ſerve them in every reſpect, without gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them the leaſt umbrage, or intermedling in any thing but the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of their Souls, and their Eccleſiaſtical Functions.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="part">
                     <head>III.</head>
                     <p>But that what I have hitherto ſaid, and ſhall ſay hereafter may be the better underſtood, we muſt conſider that there are three ſorts of Jeſuites.</p>
                     <p>The Firſt, Are certain Lay Perſons of both Sexes, who being aſſocia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with them, live under them in the practice of a certain <hi>Blind Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience,</hi> governing themſelves wholly by the Counſel of the Jeſuits, and being ready to execute all their Commands. Theſe for the moſt part are Gentlemen and Ladies, who paſs the reſt of their Lives in Widow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood; Rich Citizens and Merchants, who like good fruit-Trees, bear the Jeſuits a great quantity of precious Fruit, that is to ſay of Gold and Silver. Of this Claſs are thoſe Women who are commonly called <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gottes,</hi> who being induced by theſe Fathers to deſpiſe the World, are in exchang fleeced by them, who by their ſmooth Speeches draw from them Clothes, Moveables, and conſiderable Rents.</p>
                     <p>The ſecond ſort are only Men, of which ſome are Prieſts, and others are Layicks, who although they live in the World, and often by the interpoſition of the Jeſuits obtain Penſions, Canons, Abbies, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Revenues, have yet made a Vow to take their habit, when ever
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:54204:6"/>
the General ſhall require it. For which cauſe they are called Jeſuits <hi>in Voto.</hi> And theſe the Jeſuits uſe with a rare dexterity to eſtabliſh their <hi>Monarchy,</hi> maintaining them in the Kingdoms and Provinces, in all the Courts of Princes, and in a word, in all the conſiderable places of Chriſtendom, to the end they may ſerve them, as I ſhall ſet forth in the ſeventh Point.</p>
                     <p>The third Sort are the Politick Jeſuits, in whoſe hands all the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority reſides, who manage the Government of their Order, and who having been aſſailed with the ſame temptation Chriſt was by the Devil in the Wilderneſs, <hi>Haec omnia tibi dabo, ſi cadens adoraveris me,</hi> have ſtruck the bargain, and accepted the Condition propounded by <hi>Satan,</hi> employing all their Induſtry to reduce their <hi>Society</hi> to a <hi>perfect Monarchy.</hi> And as it is at <hi>Rome,</hi> where almoſt all the great Affairs of Chriſtianity are tranſacted, and in which place the Head of theſe brave Politicians reſides, <hi>i. e.</hi> their <hi>General,</hi> with a great number of other Perſons of the ſame Order; ſo this is the place which they have reſolved to begin their domination in, as any Man may ſee who ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveth the manner of their Conduct. It is ſcarce poſſible to propoſe an Affair in this Court, but the Jeſuits, who are informed of every thing by their Spies, worth the taking notice of, aſſemble themſelves to conclude on an Iſſue advantagious to their Intereſt; and from thence you ſhall ſee them run to the Cardinals, the Ambaſſadors, and the Prelates; where having dexterouſly inſinuated themſelves to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of the Affair then in agitation, or beginning to be ſo, they repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent it in that maner which pleaſeth them, having ever a careful reſpect to their own Intereſt, and to that purpoſe often changing the true Aſpect of things, even to the <hi>making</hi> (as the ſaying is) <hi>black white, and white black.</hi> And becauſe the firſt Relations, eſpecially when made by Religious Perſons, take a conſiderable impreſſion in the Spirits of the Hearers; from hence it proceeds that very often Affairs of great importance, which are tranſacted in the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> by Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors, and other Perſons of Authority, have not had the ſucceſs deſired by Princes; becauſe the Maſter-Jeſuits having prejudicated with their intereſted Reports the Minds of Men, have foreſtalled their Faith, and made them ſuſpicious of the Relations of others, though they were more true and ſincere. But it is not at <hi>Rome</hi> only, and with the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, that they uſe this Artifice; they practiſe it in the ſame manner, either by themſelves, or the ſecond ſort of Jeſuits, in the Courts of other Princes. From whence this conſequence will ariſe, that the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt part of the Affairs of Chriſtianity paſs through the hands of the Jeſuits, and that thoſe only ſucceed which they do not oppoſe. I af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:54204:6"/>
in the interim, that their dexterity in intrieguing in Affairs, either to hinder or promote them, being ſo ſubtile, that it may be ſaid to be impenetrable, it is impoſſible to deſcribe it exactly; but yet it is eaſy for all Princes to know it, if they will but take the pains to read what I have writ of it: For it will cauſe them to reflect upon what is paſt, and recal into their memory the particular Circumſtances of Treaties; ſo that comparing them with my Remarques, it will be almoſt impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble not to diſcover ſome part of the Craft of this admirable Society. Now though this Secret and hidden Artifice be the principal thing they put in practice to attain this Monarchic Juriſdiction, which is the principal Object of their deſires; yet this hinders them not ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times (ſo much does their Paſſion blind them) to employ other Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedients, which manifeſt their ambitious Project. For was it not a pleaſant Petition which they made under pretence of the general good of the Church, to his Holineſs <hi>Gregory</hi> the <hi>13th,</hi> that he would com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand his Legats, and all his Apoſtolic Nuntio's, to take ſome Jeſuit for their Companion and Confident, by whoſe Counſel they ſhould go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern themſelves in all their Actions.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="part">
                     <head>IV.</head>
                     <p>The fourth thing which deſerveth to be conſidered, is, That by theſe Intrigues, and by the knowledg of Affairs of State, the principal Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits have acquired the favour of many both Temporal and Spiritual Princes, making them believe they have done great Services; and from this favour great inconveniences ſpring.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Firſt,</hi> Abuſing the goodneſs and friendſhip of theſe Princes, they fear not to abuſe a great number of private Families, which, though rich, and noble, have been reduced to an extreme degree of Miſery, by the Uſurpation which the Jeſuits have made upon the Eſtates of Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, and by the unſincere Courſes, by which they have drawn into their Religion a number of thoſe young Gentlemen, which frequent their Colleges. For how often doth it happen, that theſe young Men becoming ſickly, or finding themſelves unfit for the functions of the Society, are ſent away, without reſtoring either to them or to their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations that Wealth they brought thither, and to which the Jeſuits made themſelves Heirs at their entring their Profeſſion? This Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice is far enough from the Ordinance of St. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> and from the intentions of thoſe Lords, who having founded their Houſes, did not leave them ſo much Riches as might fatiate their thirſt after the good things of this World, but rather make them fitter to ſerve the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an World.</p>
                     <p>The ſecond Inconvenience which follows this acceſs the Jeſuits have
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:54204:7"/>
to Princes, is, That they boaſt of it perpetually, and perſuade the World, that their Union and Familiarity with great Men is much greater than indeed it is, and by this means they make themſelves re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by the very Miniſters of State, who by reaſon of this do all they can to inſinuate themſelves into their good opinion; and indeed eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one hath recourſe to them to obtain what they deſire. And their vanity is arrived to that height, that they have dared to boaſt that they can make Cardinals, Nuntio's, Lieutenants, Governors, or any other Officers; yea, ſome of them have proceeded to that degree of Impudence, as to affirm that their General could do much more than the <hi>Pope;</hi> and others have added, that it is much better to be of this Order which can make Cardinals, than to be a Cardinal. I fear not that what I write ſhould make me paſs for a Slanderer, for theſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſpeak all theſe things ſo openly, that there is hardly any Perſon who converſeth with them with any degree of Familiarity, who hath not often heard the ſame things from them.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="part">
                     <head>V.</head>
                     <p>The fifth Point is, that being thus eſtabliſhed in State-practices, one of the firſt things they exact from that Prince who favours them, is, that he would permit them to advance or pull down whoever they pleaſe, ſerving themſelves always here of the pretence of Religion, that they may with the more facility obtain their ends. And if by misfortune this be granted, as it falls out too often, expect not that they ſhould fill the vacant places with Perſons of worth, who can beſt diſcharge their truſt; but on the contrary, if any ſuch happen to be recommended to that Prince, they oppoſe them with all their might, if they be not their intimate Friends, and ſuch as they know are high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affected to their Intereſt; but as for them they preſent and petition for, be they affected to the Intereſt of the Prince, or be they not, be they honeſt Men or Knaves, be they fit for the employment, or be they not, this is the leaſt part of their Care. So that it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> often ſeen, that the Officers which are choſen by theſe Men, are good for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but to vex the Prince, and exaſperate the People by Diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, which end for the moſt part in dreadful Seditions.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="part">
                     <head>VI.</head>
                     <p>The ſixth Point cannot be better repreſented than by the ſimilitude of a Maſter of a Gally, who obſerving the Wind for his turn, can no ſooner whiſtle than all the Rowers are at the Oar, to bring the Gally to the place he had before appointed: for juſt after this manner, when the General and his Aſſiſtants have once concluded that it is for their intereſt that any Perſon ſhould be advanced to any dignity, upon the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:54204:7"/>
firſt intimation of his intention to thoſe that reſide in the Provinces, there is a general attempt of all to elevate the Perſon ſo deſigned by them, into that Charge or Dignity where they would place him, ſome lifting at the Head, and ſome at the Tail, as I may ſay. Now he that hath received from them a ſervice of this nature, muſt be very ungrateful, if he denies them the like aſſiſtance when occaſion ſerves. So it often falls out, that they eſteem themſelves more obliged to the Jeſuits, than to the Prince himſelf who hath given them their prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and ſo they become more paſſionate of the Intereſt of the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits, than of the Glory and Advantage of their Maſters. Thus Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are taken for weak Perſons; and while they imagine they have got a faithful Servant, they have let in a Jeſuitical Spy, of whom they make uſe too often, to the damage of him that hath exalted him. This is as true as the reſt I have hitherto ſet forth; and it is eaſy to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port a Number of Examples, Experience furniſhing us with enough; but to avoid rendring my ſelf odious to no purpoſe, I will paſs them in ſilence, ſatisfying my ſelf with this Concluſion from what has been ſaid in this Article, That this Addreſs of the Jeſuits to introduce their Partiſans into Charges, is (it may be) the reaſon why they call their Order a <hi>Great Monarchy,</hi> becauſe by this means they govern both the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and their Miniſters. So that we need not wonder, if one of their chief Fathers, having a publick Speech to make in the name of the Society to a Prince, let ſlip theſe arrogant Words: <hi>You know, Sir, that our Order hath ever kept a good correſpondence with your Highneſs;</hi> in their imagination without doubt to be Monarchs as well as you.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="part">
                     <head>VII.</head>
                     <p>In the ſeventh place, Theſe Fathers do their utmoſt to make the World believe, that all thoſe who receive any Benefits from their Prince in what ſort ſoever, do yet obtain them by their means, or by the aſſiſtance of their Favourites. And they acquire by this way a more abſolute Empire over the minds of Subjects, than the very Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces themſelves; which it may be cannot happen without a great preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice to them, no Reaſon of State permitting that ſuch active and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious Spirits as the Jeſuits, ſhould thus diſpoſe of the Wills of their Miniſters. For beſides that by this means they can carry on obſcurely all ſorts of Treaſons and Troubles, they have alſo a certain way by theſe Miniſters their Adherents, to introduce into the Services of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces their Jeſuits <hi>in Voto,</hi> either as Counſellors, or Secretaries of State. And theſe are no ſooner received, but they fall to importune the Prince to take ſome Jeſuit, either for his Confeſſor, or Preacher: whereby both become the Spies of the General, to whom they give an exact ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:54204:8"/>
of the moſt ſecret Affairs. And from hence it comes to paſs, that what was thought moſt ſecret, is become moſt publick, when the means of its ſo being can not be diſcovered; and Deſigns of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt import are prevented, when it is impoſſible to conjecture who hath diſcovered them; and which is worſe, they are moſt often ſuſpected, who are leaſt guilty.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="part">
                     <head>VIII.</head>
                     <p>The eighth thing which we ſhould conſider here is, That as Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects do naturally follow the Inclination of their Princes; ſo all that pay obedience to the General, obſerving his Affection and Application to State-Affairs, and that he uſeth his utmoſt endeavour to enlarge and enrich by this means the Society, they by his example ſtudy Politicks, that they may be able to ſerve him in this glorious Deſign, as they eſteem it. And to this purpoſe they employ their Kindred and Friends, to ſearch the Hearts of Kings, to diſcover their moſt ſecret Intentions, never failing to give advice of them to the General, and his Aſſiſtants, ſo ſoon as they can learn the leaſt particular. For as they know this is the only way to gain the good-will of their Superiours, and bring themſelves to preferment, which is never given amongſt them to any, but what are known to be fit to elevate the Society to that Grandure they aſpire to. So they do what they can to render themſelves re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commendable by ſome Politick Act, and ſo gain the eſteem of being thought capable of the Management of greater Affairs.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="part">
                     <head>IX.</head>
                     <p>So that as by the force of Fire the Chymiſts can draw Oils, which can cure almoſt mortal Wounds; and as the induſtrious Bee extracts her Honey from the Juice of moſt different Flowers: ſo the Jeſuits, by the force of their Reaſon, extract their own Intereſt out of the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Relations are made them of all the Intereſts of the Princes, no leſs than from the ſeveral Accidents which happen in the ſeveral States; by means of which they not only allay for the time the Head of their Thirſt after Greatneſs, but gain an exact knowledg of their own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, by the help of which they obtain their end, by the good or evil Fortune of others. But that which is yet more remarkable is, that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving thus ſtollen into the heart of any Prince, they have a cuſtom of bringing them into play, or (as others ſay) ſetting them a dancing; telling them they have excellent Abilities of doing ſuch a thing, or ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting ſuch a Deſign, or finiſhing ſuch an Enterprize. But ſo ſoon as they have began to employ themſelves in favour of theſe Jeſuits, in conformity to their Promiſes, coming at laſt to conſider that ſuch an increaſe of Power in that Prince they had thus encouraged, may be
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:54204:8"/>
diſadvantageous to them, they then retard as much, as they are able, the Concluſion of that Affair; juſt like Lawyers, who prolong as much as they are able the Suits of their Clients, and then on a ſudden by a ſurpriſing Artifice, and malicious Addreſs, they perplex the Court, and entirely ruin thoſe Deſigns themſelves had inſpired. Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhall reflect on the League of <hi>France,</hi> which was treated and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded by them, and yet was abandoned when they ſaw Fortune fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured that King; and upon <hi>England,</hi> which they have promiſed ſo often to the <hi>Spaniard;</hi> ſhall be ſo convinced of the truth of this, that he ſhall never need a ſtronger proof.</p>
                     <p>May we not then draw hence this Concluſion, That the Intention of the Jeſuits being neither right nor ſincere towards any, they ſerving the World no further than their own Intereſt will permit them, neither Princes nor Prelates can employ them as Counſellors without great dammage; becauſe pretending themſelves to be equally affected to all, feigning themſelves <hi>French</hi> with the <hi>French,</hi> and <hi>Spaniards</hi> with the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and ſo with all the other Nations, as occaſion ſerves, and as the hopes of making advantage puts them on, they care not in the interim to help or hinder the one any more than the other. It is without doubt their irregular Attention to their private Intereſt, and the Neglect they have of the advancement of any other Perſon, which are the Cauſes why all thoſe Enterprizes, wherein they are concerned, have rarely ſucceeded. But then (we muſt confeſs) they have a rare Art in diſſembling this Indifference, ſome feigning themſelves very zealous Partizans of the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> others of that of <hi>Spain,</hi> others of the Empire, and ſo of all the other Princes whoſe favour they ſeek. But if among theſe Princes any one makes choice of a Jeſuit for his Confident, this man can no ſooner learn a Secret in any Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair, but he gives the General advice of it, who thereupon ſends him order how he ſhall proceed, without any regard had to the intention of that Prince, or whether they be for or againſt his Service.</p>
                     <p>Now though all the Inconveniences I have hitherto ſet forth, be extremely dammageable to the Publick, yet there are others much more ſo.</p>
                     <p>As firſt is, That the Jeſuits being thus exactly informed (as I have ſaid) of the Intereſt, and what ever elſe paſſeth in the moſt ſecret Counſels of Princes, thoſe that pretend to be of the Party of <hi>France,</hi> propoſe to the King, or to his principal Miniſters, certain Reaſons of State of great import, which have been ſent them from <hi>Rome</hi> by their great Maſters of Policy. Thoſe that pretend to be of the Party of <hi>Spain,</hi> or in any other Court where they have any acceſs, propound
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:54204:9"/>
others there, directly contrary to the firſt, or at leaſt, which can ſerve to no other purpoſe but to entertain diſtruſt amon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſt the Chriſtian Princes; ſo that they are kept in perpetual fear of each other, which diſturbs the Publick Peace more than can be expreſſed, and cauſeth great Miſeries in all Chriſtendom; ſuch a Diſtruſt being almoſt an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible Obſtacle to the Concluſion of a League againſt the common Enemy, and rendring thoſe Treaties of Peace which are made among Princes very uncertain.</p>
                     <p>The ſecond is, That by their cunning way of acting they have ſo enlightned the World, that every Man ſeems to apply himſelf moſtly to the points of State Policy; ſo that now there is no Action which is not poized in this Ballance; nor ſcarce any ordinary Affair, which is not managed according to the Jeſuits Subtilty. But that which is yet worſe, the <hi>Hereticks</hi> perceiving and imbibing the Maxims of this Society, uſe them to our great dammage, with thoſe Princes which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect them. So that whereas heretofore there were great hopes the <hi>Lutherans</hi> at leaſt ſhould one day acknowledge their Errors, now there are excellent Stateſ-men among them, and Politicians, hard to be converted.</p>
                     <p>And now that I may make it appear that I have ſaid nothing but the Truth, when I attribute extraordinary Craft and Diſſimulations to the Jeſuits, eſpecially when they deſigned to gain the favour of any Prince, I muſt not omit what they did on that account in relation to <hi>Great-Britain.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>One of that Society, called Father <hi>Perſon,</hi> the Aſſiſtant of that Kingdom, having wrote a Book againſt the Succeſſion of the King of <hi>Scotland</hi> to the Crown of <hi>England;</hi> Father <hi>Critonic,</hi> with others of the ſame Order, defended the Right of the ſaid King, by a Book entitled, <hi>The Reaſons of the King of the</hi> Scots, <hi>againſt the Opinion of Father</hi> Perſon. Now though they ſeemed to be divided among themſelves, yet they were in truth very well agreed: for this Comedy was acted by the commandment of the General, to the intent that if the Houſe of <hi>Scotland</hi> had been excluded from the Succeſſion, they might have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to him or them that had the Government <hi>Perſon</hi>'s Book; or it on the contrary, that Houſe happened to be ſettled upon the Throne, they might yet gain the King's Affection, by ſhewing him <hi>Critonic</hi>'s Book. And ſo how ever the matter fell out, they might quit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and be provided of a fit means to increaſe their Society.</p>
                     <p>By which we may obſerve alſo the truth of what I ſaid, when I af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed that Princes were the ordinary and uſual Objects of the Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions and Actions of the Jeſuits; and how much reaſon they have to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:54204:9"/>
ſay that their Order is a <hi>Great Monarchy.</hi> And is not this alſo a convict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Inſtance, and proof, of the little fear they have to diſcontent Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, when it is their Intereſt? Experience furniſheth us with a number of other Examples, which would make this as clear as the day, but I ſhould be too long and troubleſome if I ſhould repeat them here.</p>
                     <p>I will therefore inſtance in one, which is worth a thouſand, it being moſt remarkable. Every one knows there is no Perſon in the World whom the Jeſuits are more obliged to ſerve faithfully and obey than the <hi>Pope,</hi> and that not only in reſpect of that particular vow of obedience which they make to him, but alſo for a multitude of other reaſons. Yet nevertheleſs when Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the fifth, who can never be enough commended, had by the Inſpiration of the Holy Spirit, commanded them to officiate in the Quire, and make their profeſſion in the ſame manner as all the other Orders do, they never would obey him, it ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to them that they ſhould thereby receive a conſiderable prejudice. There were only ſome few who yielded their Obedience to his Holineſs his Will, and who conſented to accept the profeſſion in that manner which he had propounded: But how were they treated by the reſt? were they not in contempt call'd <hi>Avatins?</hi> And was there ever any one Perſon of theſe, who could obtain the leaſt preferment from the Society? After this manner alſo they oppoſed the famous <hi>Charles Borromee,</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Milan,</hi> who in quality of <hi>Legat à latere,</hi> would have brought their Company to the obſervance of a Religious Diſcipline.</p>
                     <p>But what is this? They obey not the holy Canons, ſeeing contrary to their Decrees, they trade in Pearls, Rubies and Diamonds, which are brought them from the <hi>Indies;</hi> and it is a common Opinion that the greateſt part of the Jewels of <hi>India,</hi> which are ſold at <hi>Venice,</hi> paſs through the hands of the Jeſuits; and we cannot imagin this is a meet Report, which hath been ſpread by their Enemies, the very Poſts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> themſelves whom they uſe, have taught it us. And I could here report ſome other things which would prove as evidently, that they are bad and unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Servants to the Pope; but becauſe I cannot do it without ſpeaking of a Prince, who will be offended at it, I will paſs it in ſilence; my deſign being to ſerve the World without offending any Man, no not the Jeſuits, whom I honour otherwiſe, and pretend not here to make an Invective againſt them, but only to abate their Pride, and teach them; if it be poſſible, a more tolerable way of acting.</p>
                     <p>For who is it that hath not juſt cauſe to complain of the Jeſuits? Yet as it often happens, that ſick Perſons ſend up their crys to Heaven, and are beheld by others in the interim with Wonder, every one per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving they are afflicted with this or that Malady, and yet but few
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:54204:10"/>
diſcern the true origin and fource of them. So though almoſt all the World complain of the Jeſuits, ſome becauſe they are perſecuted by them, others for that they are not ſerved by them with a Fidelity becoming their Habit, yet the evil continues nevertheleſs; becauſe moſt Men can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not perceive the true cauſe of ſo great a diſaſter. But if they would examine the thing a little more exactly, they ſhould eaſily find, that it is the vaſt and boundleſs deſire they have to aggrandiſe themſelves, which makes them think it a thing of no moment to diſcontent Princes or deceive them; to oppreſs the poor, to ſpoil Widows, and ruine moſt noble Families, to raiſe Jealouſies, and make Diſcords amongſt Chriſtian Princes, that by that means they may inſinuate themſelves into their greateſt Affairs. But would not this be a ſtrange diſorder in Nature, if one of the leaſt Members of the Body, and that formed to no other end than to ſerve as an Inſtrument to the more Noble, ſhould yet draw to it ſelf the pureſt Blood, and the greateſt part of the <hi>Vital Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits?</hi> the diſorder without doubt is not leſs in the Civil or Eccleſiaſtical State, while the Order of Jeſuits, which was one of the laſt that was admitted into the body of the Church, to the intent that it ſhould ſerve her in the Converſion of Infidels, and particularly in exhorting Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to repentance, on the contrary, draws to it ſelf the greateſt affairs of Princes and Prelates, that is, as I may ſay, the moſt pure and Vital Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of their Intereſt, to the end this Order may appropriate and apply them to her ſelf, though ſhe cannot do this without troubling the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of Families and Kingdoms, without oppreſſing many, whoſe riſe ſhould rather be deſired, and raiſing others, who deſerve rather to be abaſed; and finally, without thouſands of other inconveniencies which ariſe from hence.</p>
                     <p>I could eaſily produce here a great number of other reaſons, drawn from experience, beſides thoſe I have already alleged, to manifeſt That the Jeſuites ambition is of a vaſt extent, and that they have entertained an Appetite of Greatneſs, which can ſuffer no Limits or Bounds: But becauſe I affect brevity in theſe Reflections, it ſhall ſuffice to report the Project of Father <hi>Perſon</hi> upon <hi>England,</hi> in that manner he diſcovers it in his Book, intituled the <hi>Reformation of England,</hi> where having blamed Cardinal <hi>Pool</hi> (a Prelate worthy of an eternal memory, not only for his Vertue and Sanctity of Life, but alſo for his other merits to the holy Church) and obſerved certain faults and defects in the Council of <hi>Trent;</hi> at laſt he concludes, That ſuppoſing <hi>England</hi> ſhould return to the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic Faith, he would have it reduced to the form and State of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Church, that to that end all the Church Revenue ſhould be held in common, the Adminiſtration of which ſhould be committed to ſeven
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:54204:10"/>
Sages, drawn out of the Society of the Jeſuits; that they might diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute it as it ſeemed good to them. In the next place, he would have all the other Religious Orders reſtrained from returning thither under grievous Penalties, except only thoſe who live on Alms. But then, as it is ordinary for thoſe who are poſſeſt with ſelf-love, to be blinded by it, and ſo fall into the greateſt Follics, though they be otherwiſe Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, I am not at all amazed at what this Father adds: <hi>England</hi> (faith he) being once reduced to the true Faith, the Pope ought not to draw any benefit from the Church Lands for at leaſt five years, but to remit them without exception into the hands of theſe ſeven Sages, who ſhall manage them in that ſort they ſhall eſteem moſt advantagious to the Church. To ſpeak the truth, a Man muſt be very dull not to perceive, their whole deſign is to amuſe, or rather abuſe his Holineſs by ſuch a propoſition as this is, hoping at the end of theſe five years to make the ſame be confirmed by other Inventions (which do not uſe to fail them at their need) for another five years, and ſo conſequently till they have intirely excluded his Holineſs out of the Kingdom of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> Are not theſe thoughts, which point out to the Life, as in a Table, the Covetouſneſs and Ambition of the Jeſuits? Is there any man after this that can doubt of the ardent deſire they have to <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy?</hi> the Artifices they imploy to attain this, do they not evidently ſhew it too? And do they not make it appear, ſo they may obtain this, all the reſt is not worth their care, being unconcerned what profit or damage others may receive by it? But did not they in the time of <hi>Gregory</hi> the XIII<hi rend="sup">th</hi> demand the Inveſtiture of all the Churches of <hi>Rome,</hi> to begin without doubt their Empire in this Capital of the World? But that which was denied them as to <hi>Rome,</hi> hath at laſt been yielded to their importunity for <hi>England;</hi> where they have made the Dignity of <hi>Arch-Prieſt</hi> be given to a Jeſuit <hi>in voto,</hi> who inſtead of protecting the Clergy, perſecutes them like an inraged Wolf, all thoſe Prieſts who do not depend on the Jeſuits, even to the forbidding them to have any Communication one with another, or ſpeak to one another, which redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth them to diſpair. So that we need not wonder that almoſt all the Clergy of <hi>England,</hi> is at preſent Jeſuits <hi>in voto.</hi> Seing beſides the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons I have already given, no perſon is now received into the Colleges, but what have promiſed to take the habit of the Society. So that if <hi>England</hi> ſhould happen to turn to her antient Faith, it is out of doubt ſhe will give beginning to a real and perfect Jeſuitic Monarchy; becauſe the Biſhopricks, and Dignites, and generally all other Church-Revenues ſhould be given to none but Jeſuits.</p>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:54204:11"/>
                     <p>We cannot after all this think it ſtrange that ſo few Hereticks are now a days converted, eſpecially in that Kingdom we have juſt now mentioned. Firſt, becauſe the antient Clergy, which once had there good ſucceſs, which the Jeſuits falſly attributed to themſelves, is almoſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely extinct. For as for the Jeſuits, they had rather attend their own intereſt, than apply themſelves to the Salvation of Souls. Secondly, becauſe the Hereticks perceiving the oppreſſion which the Catholic Prieſts ſuffer on the part of the Jeſuits, and the Artifices which they uſe in all their undertakings, have ſo great an averſion for it, that to avoid the tyranny of ſuch People, they think of nothing leſs than Converſion. I will ſay nothing here of their imaginary Pretences to a certain Eſtate, nor of thoſe diſcourſes they jade the Ears of a Prince with, touching the Authority they boaſt of over the Spirits of their People, by the means of which they pretend to be able to retain them in their Obedience, and render them well affected to their Governors. I will therefore content my ſelf for a concluſion of this Diſcourſe, to propound four Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, with which I will conclude theſe Remarks.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="1" type="consideration">
                     <head>I.</head>
                     <p>That Men of that Ambition, and of thoſe aſpiring Deſigns which the Jeſuits are of, are always Lovers of Change; ſo that being able to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce them every moment, by the help of Arms, in the management of which we have made it appear they are ſo expert, it is almoſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible they ſhould abſtain from it. From whence any Man muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude they ought not to be very dear to any Prince that loves Peace, and the preſervation of his State, ſeeing they can do him no Service (as I have before ſaid) which he may not expect from many others, when they may on the other ſide cauſe him a thouſand troubles; it being to be feared that they may hazard his State, if ſuffering them in his Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, he doth not favour them, and govern himſelf by their direction, in which nevertheleſs there is an equal danger attends him, for the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons we have declared in the preſent Points.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="consideration">
                     <head>II.</head>
                     <p>If without the leaſt temporal Jurisdiction they cauſe ſo great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions in the World, what would follow if by misfortune one of them ſhould be choſen Pope? We cannot doubt but he would fill the <note n="*" place="margin">Conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſtory.</note> Conclave with Jeſuits, which would be a means to perpetuate the Popedom in that Society. Moreover, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning themſelves as they do, according to the Rules of their own pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Intereſt, and having the Popes power on their ſide with all his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, is it not much to be feared they would endanger the States of many Princes, eſpecially thoſe that lay next the Eccleſiaſtic States?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="consideration">
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:54204:11"/>
                     <head>III.</head>
                     <p>A Pope of their Society would doubtleſs uſe his utmoſt endeavour to put them in poſſeſſion of ſome temporal Juriſdiction, or ſtrong Town, which he could never do without injuring ſome other Prince.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="consideration">
                     <head>IV.</head>
                     <p>If the Conſiſtory were once filled with Jeſuits, all the Patrimony of the Church, all the Revenues of the Holy Church would be in their hands; and as we ſee the more an Hydropick drinks, the more his thirſt increaſeth; ſo it were to be feared theſe Fathers, with all their grandeur, being every day worſe than other, corrupted by the Riches and Honours of the World, would cauſe innumerable Revolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Now every one knows there is nothing more capable of Change than States, eſpecially if there be People bold enough to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt it. So that taking the Caſe as I have put it, there is great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability the Jeſuits would alter the preſent Government, and reduce it to their own, that ſo they might make it by that means an effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Monarchy. For though hitherto notwithſtanding all their efforts to attain a real apparent Monarchy, by alluring to them the Sons of ſome Sovereign Prince, who might put them in poſſeſſion of his State, yet they never could effect it, other Princes, who knew their Deſigns, oppoſing it. But if a Jeſuit ſhould happen to be Pope, they being then without difficulty Maſters of the Eccleſiaſtic State, would certainly by the means of their ſubtil Inventions attain the end they have ſo long propounded to themſelves. But if we were ſure the Plot would fail, yet the Suſpicions and Fears of many, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the neighbouring Princes, ought to be duly conſidered, and make the Electors of the Pope narrowly watch a point of that great import.</p>
                     <p>We may draw this general Concluſion from all that hath been ſaid, That it is neceſſary for the preſervation of the public Peace, and the ſafety of all Kingdoms, that his Holineſs the <hi>Pope,</hi> with the aſſiſtance of other <hi>Chriſtian Princes,</hi> do aſſign ſome Bounds to this So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, whoſe Ambition is now mounted to an incredible both diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and exceſs, for fear the Remedy being delayed, the Miſchief ſhould become incurable.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="18" facs="tcp:54204:12"/>
And when my Advice ſhall be asked touching the means fit to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate the Paſſions of theſe Fathers, I hope to acquit my ſelf in that manner, that they ſhall be ſo far from being offended, that they ſhall have juſt reaſon to give me thanks; my Deſign being to render them the Monarchs of Souls, which are the Treaſures of Jeſus Chriſt, and not of the World, which is but Dirt. I ſay, I offer my ſelf to this Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment out of Charity, with an intent to contribure to it all thoſe Powers it hath pleaſed God to give me.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Cologne,</hi> by <hi>Jean le Blanc.</hi>
                     </signed> 
                     <dateline>
                        <date>1678.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:54204:12"/>
                  <head>THE SECRET DIRECTIONS OF THE Society of the <hi>JESUITS.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <head type="sub">Endeavoured to be tranſlated from a <hi>French</hi> Copy, Printed at COLON, 1678.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <p>There is nothing covered, that ſhall not be revealed; and hid, that ſhall not be known.</p> 
                        <bibl>St. Matth. 10. 26.</bibl>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>An ADVICE.</head>
                     <p>SOme Years ſince, a Duke of <hi>Brunswick,</hi> who call'd himſelf <hi>Biſhop of Haverſtead;</hi> having plunder'd the Jeſuits College at <hi>Paderborn,</hi> made a Preſent of their Library, and of all their Papers to the <hi>Capu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chins,</hi> who found this ſecret <hi>Inſtruction,</hi> amongſt the Memoirs of the Rector of the College: (And many worthy Perſons have aſſured us, that the like happened to the College of Jeſuits at <hi>Prague.)</hi> But however this be, how little ſoever any mans acquaintance with the Jeſuits be, he cannot doubt but that the Heads of this Order receive from their General theſe ſorts of ſecret Inſtructions, ſeeing experience tells us their Actions and Practices are conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant and perfectly agreeable to the Advices and Maxims of this little Book. But which is yet much more deplorable is, that theſe private Directions are quite contrary to the Rules, Conſtitutions, and Inſtructions, which this Society profeſſeth publickly in thoſe Books it hath printed on this Subject; So that without difficulty we may believe that the greateſt part of their Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:54204:13"/>
(if a very few be excepted eſpecially) have a double Rule, as well as a double Habit: one for their private and particular uſe, and another to flant with in publick before the World. A Rule like the Devil forwithin, and another like a Saint for without. In this like the Phariſees, to whom our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt gave this Reproof, <hi>Ye are like whited Sepulchers which appear fair to the eyes of men, and whoſe outſide is full of won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Beauty; But yet within are fill'd with nothing but dead Men's bones, ſtench and ill ſavours;</hi> indeed to M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n you ſeem honeſt perſons, though all within be nothing but Hypocriſie and Wickedneſs. But to the end all the World may be convinced that what I have ſet forth is no Calumny, but a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid Truth, I ask but this, that a little reflection might be made on the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches of <hi>Claudius Aquaviva,</hi> one of their Generals, ſo often repeated, againſt the Superiors of this Society; which is, that all the baſe Crimes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in great Mens Courts by them, that all their Intrigues, and the Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie which is inſeparable from them, proceed wholly from hence, that under pretence of advancing the Glory of God, and the Salvation of Men, they ſought nothing but themſelves. And now, dear Reader, this being ſo, I believe this little Collection of Rules, and the moſt ſecret Maxims of their Society, ought to be conſidered as a very precious <hi>depoſitum</hi> (and without making compariſons) of the nature of that which the Apoſtle recommends to <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi> when he charges him, <hi>Keep that which I have committed to thy truſt, and reveal it not but to faithful and truſty Perſons.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="1" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:54204:13"/>
                     <head>CHAP. I. <hi>What muſt be done upon our firſt entry and ſettlement in any place?</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p n="1">1. TO render our Religion acceptable and welcome to the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the places we ſettle in, it is very neceſſary to tell them that our Rule and Conſtitution have no other aim, but the Salvation of our own Souls and theirs. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is fit with great reverence and humility to reſort to the Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, and viſit frequently the Sick, and them in Priſon, to take their Confeſſions, that ſo by a Charity unknown to other Religious Orders towards the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>or, and alſo by means of our new Entry, thoſe that are the beſt and higheſt of the place, may have us in veneration and reverence.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. We ſhould remember the written Rule, which enjoins us to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand modeſtly and religiouſly a permiſſion to perform our Exerciſes; and alſo to ſeek the good-will as well of great Church-men, as Seculars, whoſe Favour and Authority we ſtand in need of.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Going to places diſtant from our habitation, or viſiting them that are nearer, they ſhould ſeek the leaſt Alms which are deſtinated to the Poor, that the Inhabitants being thus made acquainted with our Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, may be the more liberal to us.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. We muſt have one and the ſame Spirit and Deſign as to the external appearance, that by a ſeeming very humble Conformity, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one may be brought to believe our Religion is good. And ſuch of our Order, who obſerve not this Maxim, ought to be diſmiſs'd for this only reaſon.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. It is our Intereſt to encreaſe our Revenue and Wealth rather by Liberality than Purchaſe; and if we buy any Goods, Houſes, or other things uſeful to us, the Purchaſe muſt be in the Name of ſome third Perſon, who is well affected to us, that by that means we may be thought the poorer.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. Thoſe Revenues which we have near thoſe Places we live in, ſhould be aſſigned by our Provincial to other Colleges more diſtant, that neither the King, nor the People, may ever know either the quantity or the quality of our Revenue.</p>
                     <p n="7">
                        <pb n="22" facs="tcp:54204:14"/>
7. Let none of ours ſettle themſelves, but in rich and wealthy places.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. Let the Intention of the Society be in this an imitation of our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, who went not to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and other places, but to ſave Souls; he knew <hi>Judea,</hi> becauſe he converſed there fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently with his Diſciples.</p>
                     <p n="9">9. If the Society chiefly intends the Salvation of Souls, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb will be verified by them, <hi>Where People is, Prey is to be had.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="10">10. Not only for our profit, but alſo to make it appear that we are poor, we ought to ſearch out, and get whatever is or ſeemeth to be ſuperfluous in any place.</p>
                     <p n="11">11. Let ours preach according to the manners of the People they converſe with, and whiſper it ſweetly in their ears, that they are come to catechiſe the Children <hi>gratis,</hi> without exception of any Perſon, and yet do all according to the intention of the Order, and not ſeem in the leaſt a Burthen to the People, as all the other Religious Orders of <hi>Mendicants</hi> are.</p>
                     <p n="12">12. Let them not declare themſelves of the number of other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious <hi>Mendicants,</hi> till our Houſe be ſufficiently endowed, and of this we ought to be very careful.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. II. <hi>What ought to be done to procure the Ear and Familiarity of Princes and Great Men.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p n="1">1. WE ought to be mighty careful here, in gaining the Ear of Princes, quelling the preſumption of them who think they have no need of us, and do our utmoſt that all may depend upon us, and that no Perſon what ever may be ſo hardy as to lift up himſelf againſt us.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Always when Princes know their Actions odious, they deſire to have the Fathers of the Jeſuits about them, who never reprove them, but expound them in the beſt ſence, which may be obſerved in Marria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges contracted with their Kindred, which are ever ill thought of by the People, <hi>quòd tales execrantur Thoros.</hi> And therefore when Princes affect ſuch or the like things, we ought to animate their Spirits, and make them more affected to them, giving hopes that we can eaſily ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:54204:14"/>
from the Pope what ever we will, repeating ſome Reaſons, Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, or Examples, which may augment their deſires, ſeeing ſuch Marriages have been approved for the common Good, though of great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Conſequence; and laſtly, that they are allowed to Princes, for the greater Glory of God.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. So when a Prince undertaketh any thing, for example, a War, we ought to ſpur him on, encouraging him to Conſtancy, without ever conſidering the Cauſe, for fear the ill event ſhould be imputed to us; and if it falls not out well, then to tell them that our Rule forbids us to intermeddle in ſuch things.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. To content Princes, and preſerve their Friendſhip, it is not amiſs to go upon ſome Ambaſſies, provided they be advantagious to us; and ſo make our ſelves no leſs neceſſary than acceptable, by ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them that we have great power with the Pope, and other Princes.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. There is no better way to gain the Affections of Princes, and their Courtiers, than to make, or cauſe Preſents to be made to them we diſcover to be in their favour, to the end that <hi>(ſt aliàs nequeant)</hi> they may acquaint us with the Affections, Manners, and Delights of the Prince, and thoſe whom he hateth; how he acteth, and what his Cuſtoms are. And this being known, we ſhall the better inſinuate our ſelves into the Spirits of Princes and Great Men; who if they be not married, we ought in taking their Confeſſions to ſpeak to them of Marriages with Noble, Beautiful, and Rich Ladies, which if they be not of the Kindred of any of our Friends, yet at leaſt let them be of our familiar acquaintance, pointing out to them, by Commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons conformable to the Deſigns and Wills of thoſe Princes and Great Men, the Virgins we recommended. And ſo by the Women it may happen, that we ſhall gain the Love of them who are not of our Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. And this is ſeen by experience in the Houſe of <hi>Auſtrich,</hi> and in the Kingdoms of <hi>Poland</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> and in many other Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palities.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. If Women who often change their Opinions, freely put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into our hands, we ought ſeriouſly to imprint in them a great Love for our Society, and make them to puſh it on in that Affection, not only by our own, but thoſe alſo of their private Families, that they may the more earneſtly ſeek our Advancement. And we may gain this Love by divers little Services, and ſmall Preſents, yea, and diſcover the greateſt Secrets of the Lady, who will not fail to reveal them to us her ſelf, if we uſe theſe means, and then ſhe will remain always firm to us.</p>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:54204:15"/>
                     <p n="7">7. In governing the Conſciences of great Men, we ought to follow the Opinion of thoſe who have ſpoken with the greateſt Liberty, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the ſentiment of the Monks, that ſo they being rejected, Princes may follow our Advice and Counſels, and ſo all may be at our diſcretion, and depend entirely upon us.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. And to this purpoſe, to gain the Friendſhip of Princes, Prelates, and other great Men, it is very pertinent to render them Partakers of the Merits of our Order, ſhewing them how conſiderable we are in all the World, and that our Powers are great and large to abſolve in reſerved Caſes, which the other Orders have not; as, (1.) To diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence with faſting: (2.) With reſtoring what is due to another: (3.) To diſſolve the hinderances of Marriages, and of all ſorts of Vows which leſſen our Liberty.</p>
                     <p n="9">9. We ought to beget Enmities and Quarrels amongſt great Men, popular Commotions, and what ever we believe agreeable to Princes, following their Wills in every thing.</p>
                     <p n="10">10. But if any Perſon of Credit, who poſſeſſeth the next place to any Monarch, be againſt us, and yet the Prince grants him any favour, or confers Honours at his requeſt, we muſt wait on him, court him at the greateſt height imaginable, both by Viſits, Humility, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. III. <hi>What ought to be done in relation to thoſe Lords which are not rich, but yet have great Authority in the Common-wealth, that by their Credit we obtain Profit and Preferment.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p n="1">1. IF theſe Lords be Seculars, we ought to have recourſe to their Aid and Friendſhip againſt our Adverſaries, and to their favour in our own Suits, and thoſe of our Friends; and to their Authority and Power, in the purchaſe of Houſes, Mannors, and Gardens, and of Stones to build with, eſpecially in thoſe places which will not endure to hear of our ſettling in them; becauſe the Authority of theſe Lords ſerveth very much for the appeaſing of the Populace, and making our Ill-willers quiet.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. We ought to take care, that the Prelates and their Dioceſans may venerate and reverence us, that ſo they may not hinder our Exerciſes
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:54204:15"/>
in thoſe places where they have power. For in <hi>Germany, Poland,</hi> and <hi>France</hi> the Biſhops have a great Authority; who with a little trouble<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> being Patrons, may obtain for us of the Prince what is neceſſary for us; as Monaſteries, Pariſhes pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>te, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>priate, Altars, pious Lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and other things, after having given ſome ſmall ſatisfaction to thoſe Secular Prieſts who ſhall co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ey to us ſome Fou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ions<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> we may eaſily accompliſh in thoſe places where <hi>Catholicks</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> mixt with <hi>Hereticks</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticks.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3. We ought to ſhew theſe Prelats, that beſides the Merit, they ſhall receive thereby a great benefit; whereas from the Secular Prieſts and other Monks they can expect nothing <hi>preter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="4">4. It is fit to commend their Zeal, immortalized by the memory of ſo great an Action, if by their means we obtain the Benefites and Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Secular Prieſts and Canons, which they may eaſily effect by the means and favour of thoſe Biſhops.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. We ought to be very careful when any Biſhop founds a College, that we may have the power to preſent a Vicar to the Pariſh Church, with cure of Souls, though the Superiors themſelves ſhould for ſome time execute the Function of Curate, to the end that all the Regiment, and Adminiſtration of the Church may be at our Power and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. We muſt take care that the Biſhops may build us Colleges i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> thoſe Places where the Univerſities are againſt us, and where both Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks and Hereticks hinder us from having any foundation, and that as well in theſe places, as in other noble Towns we may in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to them have the Liberty of preaching before all others.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. When any of our Order are to be Canonized, we ought to obtain the ſame by Letters of Recommendation addreſs'd by great Men to the See of <hi>Rome;</hi> if upon this occaſion it happens that it be neceſſary that theſe great Men ſhould ſollicit the ſame in Perſon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> we muſt be careful that they be not attended, nor neceſſitated to make uſe of any Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Perſons with whom we have no communication, for fear the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection they have for us ſhould turn on their ſide; and that in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces where their Eſtates are, and where our Colleges are ſituate, they ſhould give themſelves into the hands of other Religions Orders, to our loſs and dammage. And therefore when any Illuſtrious Perſon comes into the places where we have Colleges, we ought to receive them with all the Modeſty and Religion that is poſſible.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:54204:16"/>
                     <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>The Duty of the Preachers, and Confeſſors of Princes and Great Men.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p n="1">1. THat Princes, Lords, and other great Men, may be perfectly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed by us, and in that manner, that they may know that our Intention and Aim is the bringing greater Glory to God, which our Society hath choſen for its Badge and true Symbol, and which we will preſerve with all ſincerity; <hi>viz.</hi> If Princes will follow our Counſel, we muſt not preſently, but by little and little ſee to the Government and Adminiſtration of their Revenues, Poſſeſſions, and Eſtates; and that we may obtain this, we muſt frequently imprint upon their Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, that they ought not to diſtribute Honours, Charges, Offices, and Dignities, to any but thoſe that are worthy and capable of them, and who have well deſerved them by their good Services.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. That whoever doth otherwiſe, commits a great Offence againſt God. But yet we muſt not ſeem to have any deſign, that any of ours ſhould intermeddle in the Adminiſtration of the Common-wealth, but rather let them proteſt the contrary as ſolemnly as they can poſſibly, only that they are obliged to ſpeak the truth by reaſon of their Charges.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. But if the Prince falls into any doubt and fear, then we muſt ſet forth what are the Qualifications and Vertues neceſſary for them that are to fill ſuch places, and what their Duty is. And great Care is to be taken, that no Perſon be admitted, if he be not one of our intimate Friends. And let Princes be taught, that the emploiment of Perſons of Honeſty, and good Life, is very honourable and requiſite for the good of the Church and State, who ought to be nominated to the Prince, not by thoſe we ſuſpect, but by our intimate and faithful Friends; for in ſo doing both of them will have a great obligation to us, and ſo will hold themſelves more engaged and bound to the Services they at all times do us.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. The Confeſſors and Preachers ought to inform themſelves of our Confidents in all parts of the Kingdom, what is the wealth of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, if they be endowed with Power and Liberality; keeping an exact Liſt of their Names and Surnames; recommending them finely and dexterouſly to Princes, that they may the more eaſily, when occaſion ſerves, be provided with Charges, according to their Dignity and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts;
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:54204:16"/>
and chiefly thoſe, whom the Confeſſors and Preachers have in their Confeſſions and Converſations obſerved to be much affected to our Society.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. Above all, let the Confeſſors and Preachers remember to treat Princes and others ſweetly and pleaſantly, not to extort any thing from them in their Confeſſions, be it either at publick or private Sermons. Let ours that are in the Service of Princes, keep but a very little Money, and a few Moveables, contenting themſelves with a little Chamber, modeſtly keeping company with the moſt vile and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject Perſons, but without Flattery; and ſo being in good eſteem, they ought prudently to perſuade Princes not to do any thing without their Counſel, whether it be in Spiritual or Temporal Affairs.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. There muſt be great care taken, ſpeedily and in good time to know the Names of the Officers of the Common-wealth, to change them, and preſently put others into their places; which muſt be ſo managed, that it may not be thought that the Change comes by our means, but that it be done in the moſt ſecret manner that can be.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. V. <hi>What is to be done in relation to thoſe Religious Orders, which agreeing with us in many things, on many occaſions draw to themſelves that which ſhould have appertained to us?</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p n="1">1. WE ſhould bear this ſort of Men, though againſt our Wills, and therefore we ſhould endeavour to imprint upon the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of thoſe Princes who love us, that our Order is more perfect than all other Orders; and that if others excell in their Functions, ours do yet appear in a more eminent degree in the Church of God; that alſo the Rules of all other Orders are entirely ſubject to ours.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. We ought to remark the Defaults of other Orders, and make it appear, that thoſe who ſtand in competition with us, cannot ſucceed ſo proſperouſly in their Affairs as we.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. We ought to oppoſe more violently thoſe Orders who intermeddle in the Education of Youth, in imitation of us, eſpecially in thoſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where it is our intereſt to teach with applauſe, and in which we gain a conſiderable profit.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. We ought to repreſent to the Prince and his Counſel, that thoſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:54204:17"/>
Orders may beget Tumults and Seditions in the Common-wealth, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they beget Factions in it. And we ought to repreſent to the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities, that the other Orders are nearer to their ruine than we; and if they have Letters of Recommendation from the Pope, or any of the Cardinals, which maintain them, we muſt have recourſe to the favour of Princes with the Pope, remonſtrating that our Society is maintained, eſtabliſhed, and fortified by more Authentic Letters and Titles.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. It is fit that we have a good report in thoſe Towns where we have our Colleges, who may be induced to certify our Inſtitution, honeſt Life, and the Benefit the Youth receive under our tuition.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. And in the interim we ought to inſinuate with great Art, that * Contrarieties and Tumults are to be feared from the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of Schools, which are ſuffered, and from the Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers <note place="margin">Oppoſitions.</note> which are eſtabliſhed in them; and that they being Religious Perſons, the Tumults will be the greater.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. We ought to employ our utmoſt care that Learning may flouriſh with great applauſe to us, rendring to Princes, our Superiors, and the very People, great Proofs and Teſtimonies of vertue.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Of the Means to acquire the Friendſhip of Rich Widows.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p n="1">1. WE ought for this purpoſe to chooſe thoſe Fathers that are of a lively countenance, and middle Age, who muſt often viſit their Houſes; and if they expreſs any kindneſs for our Society, make them partakers of the Merits of it. And then if they begin to frequent our Churches, it is fit to give them Confeſſors who may diſpoſe them to perpetuate their Widow-hood, repreſenting to them the Delights, Pleaſures, and Wealth, they ſhall enjoy, if they continue in that ſtate; which we muſt promiſe, <hi>tanquam Obſides,</hi> that they ſhall have an eternal Reward for it, and that by this ſole means they may exempt themſelves from the pains of Purgatory.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. We ought to ſtir them up to the getting of an Oratory, and an Altar well adorned, about which employing all their care, they may baniſh all thoughts of them who may ſeek them in marriage; and if they have a little Chappel, we ought to celebrate Maſs there very fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, and above all things make ſome ſhort Exhortations there.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. That things may ſucceed the better, it is fit to perſuade them to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:54204:17"/>
diminiſh their Train and Families, appointing them what Officer they ſhal have, and Perſons for the management of their Eſtates, and to introduce artificially and inſenſibly thoſe that ſhall be neceſſary for the Government of their Houſes, according to the degree of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, their Place, Affection, and Devotion to our Society, changing their Officers to put in others at our Devotion and Diſcretion.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. The firſt thing the Confeſſor hath to do, is to perſuade them to acquieſce in their Counſel, and to ſubmit themſelves entirely to them, as the only Foundation of all that Spiritual Good they can receive.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. To propound the frequent uſe of the Communion, aſſiſting at the Divine Service, reciting of Letanies, and to make a daily examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Conſcience, in which they ought to help them, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade them to chuſe ſome Saint for their Tutelar Patron, and eſpecially to recommend to them our holy Founder.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. Exhort them to make a general Confeſſion, ſo that knowing their former Accuſations, Manners, and Inclinations, the whole may ſerve as a Guide to make them obey our Wills.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. To exhort them twice or thrice a week concerning the Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity which they receive in their Widow-hood, concerning the Troubles, Dangers, and Charges, that will attend a ſecond Marriage.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. Being thus diſpoſed to continue in that ſtate, we ought forthwith to perſuade them to enter ſome Cloiſter, but then ſuch an one as <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ulina,</hi> that being engaged in a Vow of Chaſtity, they never marry again, we ought ſtrongly to perſuade them to forſake the Society of younger Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who are given to Recreations, Poetry, and Muſick, and that they ſhould ſuffer few Perſons to ſee them, and that they ſhould obſerve in treating ſuch a moderate Modeſty, for fear ſuch ſhould complain that they are too rudely uſed, and ſo ours ſhould be blamed or reproved.</p>
                     <p n="9">9. That the Officers of their Manors, Chaplains, Curates, and all others, may be admitted to their Functions upon our recommendation, and that they may depend entirely upon our Wills.</p>
                     <p n="10">10. When we have obtained this, then we are by little and little to diſpoſe them to give Alms, and do good works, repreſenting to them that without this they cannot attain the Kingdom of Heaven; which Alms notwithſtanding they ought not to diſpoſe to every one, if it be not by the advice, and with the conſent of their Spiritual Father. And for as much as it is of great import that this be well managed, as to the Perſon, that they may receive a recompence from God, it is neceſſary to let them know, that Alms ill diſpoſed do rather hurt than good. And if they underſtand not that it is a good proficiency, and for the expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of their Sins, yet we ought not to allow them ſo much Liberty and Liberality.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:54204:18"/>
                     <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>Of the means of keeping in our hands the diſpoſition of the Eſtates of Widows.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p n="1">1. WIdows ſhould be frequently ſolicited to perſevere in their Devotions, and do good Works, and not to ſuffer one week to paſs without ſome act of Charity of their own free will, in imitation of the holy Virgin; and that cutting off all ſuperfluous Expences, they ſhould give ſome conſiderable thing to the Poor, and to the Church of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. If after this, they become liberal to our Society, as by giving ſome conſiderable ſum of Money; then we ought to make them abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute partakers of the Merits of our Society; and that every thing may have the greater ſhew, and have the greater force, this ought to be done by our Provincial, or General.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. If theſe Widdows have made a Vow of Chaſtity; Let them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new it betwixt the hands of their Confeſſors twice every year, that ſo they may think themſelves, ſo much the more ſtrictly bound by the renewing of their Vows to preſerve that friendſhip they have entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for our Society; permitting them to rejoice and recreate themſelves conveniently the day of this renewing them.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. We ought to propound to them a rule of Life, and that if it be acceptable to themſelves, they ought to make their Family and Servants ſubmit to it.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. Propound a monthly Confeſſion to them on the Feaſts which are ſolemnized in memory of our Lord, of the holy Virgin, of the Apoſtles, and of the Patron or tutelary Saint, which they have choſen, but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of St. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> and St. <hi>Xavier.</hi> We ought alſo to give them <hi>Sindies;</hi> which may have an Eye upon both the Men and Women of their Family; and obſerve their defaults, that ſo we may know whatever paſſeth, concealing in the interim their Vow of Chaſtity.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. We ought to enjoin their Servants, both Men and Women, not to uſe any leering or disdainful Looks, or to ſpeak and look another way, which ends for the moſt part in contempt; and to ſee that they who are taken in theſe faults be ſeverely chaſtiſed, or rather forthwith turn'd away with the Widows conſent.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. Our next care muſt be, That they may be ſerved by honeſt Maids,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:54204:18"/>
admitted upon our recommendation; and that care be taken they may be expert in making Church Ornaments for us, that ſo our Widows may live with the greater piety.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. We muſt appoint theſe Maidens a Governeſs of our own Sort, who may make them continually to work, and obſerve their Actions.</p>
                     <p n="9">9. We ought to viſit theſe Widows frequently, provided theſe Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſits be not troubleſome; entertaining them with pleaſant Diſcourſes, and holy Stories; keeping them always pleaſant, according to their ſeveral humors, and never treat them rigorouſly in Confeſſions, for fear they become thereby diſaffected to us, except when there is little hope of making any advantage of them.</p>
                     <p n="10">10. We ought to conſolate them, and diſpoſe them to confeſs often, that by this conſolation they may wholly confide in us, and turn all their Eſtates into our hands.</p>
                     <p n="11">11. It is of great import for the preſerving and increaſing the friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of Widows, to allow them the priviledg of entring our Colleges, at the time of the ſolemn Acts and Tragedies and other ſuch like, and not to ſuffer them to go out of their Houſes in the depth of Winter; to diſpence with them for Faſting and Sackcloth, which they compenſate by Alms, that ſo they may ſee we have no leſs care of the health of their Bodies than of their Souls.</p>
                     <p n="12">12. But if there be any hope that we ſhall gain any thing more by frighting them, then we ought to treat them more rudely, and here the Confeſſor muſt make uſe of great Prudence, when he hath firſt conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of it with the Superior.</p>
                     <p n="13">13. We ought to keep them as much as is poſſible, from viſiting the Churches of the other Religious Orders, at the Feaſts which they ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize, and therefore we ought effectually to repreſent to them, that all the Indulgences of all the other Orders are infuſed and compriſed in the Rule of our Society.</p>
                     <p n="14">14. We ought to permit them all manner of Senſuality; provided they be liberal, and well affected to our Society, and conſtant in the ſame; and that all things be carried cunningly, and without ſcandal.</p>
                     <p n="15">15. When any diſcourſe is concerning their Eſtates; We ought to ſet before them the perfect eſtate of the Saints, who have parted with their Lives, their Kindred, and Friends with a chearful heart, that they might aſſiſt the poor; who are the Members of Jeſus Chriſt, and now is the time to tell them what glorious Crowns they ſhall enjoy, if they will reſign themſelves and their Eſtates, into the hands of our Society.</p>
                     <p n="16">16. To diſpoſe them the more eaſily to this; we ought to ſhew them the 1, 2, 3 &amp; 4, Articles of our Conſtitutions, that ſo they may under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:54204:19"/>
the beginning of that perfection, which conſiſts in re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>cing all irregular affections to our kindred, and acting ſo that whatever we do may tend to the glory of God, being governed by the Counſels of our Spiritual Fathers, and the fears of Death, which often is inflicted as a puniſhment of our too great love to our Blood. We ought to perſuade them, that this ought to be a true reſignation, and intire remiſſion of all they have into our hands, which we thus often and ſeriouſly ſeek; which yet is unknown to all other Orders. We ought to recount the Examples of others, who by this ſole reſignation, have acquired the Kingdom of Heaven; and give them hopes they ſhall be one day ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noniſed; if they will effectually do this: Promiſing them alſo under the Seal of Confeſſion, that our Authority with the S. <hi>See of Rome;</hi> ſhall never be wanting to them upon ſo glorious an Account.</p>
                     <p n="17">17. And therefore when the Widows are thus diſpoſed to reſign their Eſtates into our hands, and to follow the Counſel of their Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Fathers, they ought preſently to avoid murmuring and Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, to confirm this Reſignation, if they may be well brought to it, and if they will believe firmly that this Counſel is given them by God, the Protector of Widows, who is more careful of their Souls than of their Bodies.</p>
                     <p n="18">18. We ought to imprint ſeriouſly on their Spirits, that God is greatly pleaſed with thoſe good Works and Alms which they give to Religious Perſons, and thoſe who live holily.</p>
                     <p n="19">19. That this muſt be by the Advice and Counſel of their Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, making them underſtand that thoſe pious Works which are free, are always acceptable before God, when they are accompanied with Obedience, which is the Siſter of Humility; but then they are to tell whom they intend to give to, and they muſt give in a bill of them to their Confeſſor, that he may add, diminiſh, or change them, as he ſees cauſe.</p>
                     <p n="20">20. But above all things, we ought to forbid our Widows the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation of other Religious Perſons, for fear they ſhould draw in our devout Women; for the moſt part this Sex is inconſtant, and to that end we muſt repreſent, that our Order is the greateſt, and of the greateſt profit to the Church, of the greateſt Credit in all places, and of the greateſt Authority with Princes, and that it is impoſſible to chuſe a better; which is not to be expected from Monks, who take no care of the Salvation of Souls, and are for the moſt part ignorant, dull, addicted to their Bellies, and all ſorts of pleaſures.</p>
                     <p n="21">21. After we have thus drawn from our Widows a good quantity of Money and Goods, for fear they ſhould entertain any thoughts of a
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:54204:19"/>
ſecond Marriage, we ought to aſſign them dexterous Confeſſors, who may take care to procure them to aſſign us ſome annul Penſions or Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes, or Alms, to enable us to pay the ſtanding Charges of our Colleges, and profeſt Houſes, eſpecially that of the City of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Cell, where thoſe of our Society, who are poor, ſtudy; as for ſettling Noviti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ats, who have been a long time diſperſed; and alſo to diſpoſe them to beſtow yearly a Sum of Money, for the buying of Copes, Chalices, and other Ornaments for the Altar.</p>
                     <p n="23">23. Before theſe Widows come to die, if they have not entirely reſigned up all they have, be it by reaſon of their fear of their Kindred, or for any other cauſe, we ought to acquaint them with our poverty, the quantity of our Colleges which are not yet endowed, the Devotion and great number of our Religious Perſons, the neceſſities of our Churches, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting them to contribute to the finiſhing of our Colleges which are yet imperfect, for the greater glory of God, giving us Lamps and Pixes, and for the building of other Foundations and Houſes, which we the poor Servants of the Society of <hi>Jeſus</hi> do ſtill want, that all things may be perfected.</p>
                     <p n="24">24. Let the ſame be done with Princes, and our other Benefactors, who build us any ſumptuous Pile, or erect any Foundation, repreſenting to them in the firſt place, that the Benefits they thus do us are conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Eternity; that they ſhall become thereby perfect Models of Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; that we will have thereof a very particular memory; and that in the next World they ſhall have their Rewards. But if it be objected, that Jeſus Chriſt was born in a Stable, and had not where to lay his Head; and that we who are his <note n="*" place="margin">This very inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Word is in the Original.</note> 
                        <hi>Compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> ought not to enjoy periſhing Goods. We ought to imprint ſtrongly on their Spirits, that in truth at firſt the Church was alſo in the ſame ſtate, but now that by the Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God ſhe is raiſed to a <hi>Monarchy;</hi> and that in thoſe times the Church was nothing but a <hi>broken Rock,</hi> which is now become a <hi>great Mountain.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>Of the means of drawing to us the Sons and Daughters of our devout Widows.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p n="1">1. THat Mothers may the more eaſily bring this to paſs, we ought to imprint this upon their Spirits, that they ought to be rigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to thoſe Daughters which are contrary to their Wills, chaſtiſing
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:54204:20"/>
them with Rods if they be young; with Mortifications, and threats of worſer uſage for the future, if they be grown too big for the former; and ſo proceed to puniſh them, by not giving them the Ornaments befit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their portion and quality. But if they accept our Religion, then they ought to ſhew them more kindneſs, and promiſe them a better Fortune than if they were married.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Their Mothers ought to repreſent to them the fury of an Husband, which may be a burthen to them in their future Marriage; the difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and troubles of that State of Life, telling them the Anguiſh and Torments they endured in their Marriage, which hath brought them nothing but ſorrow; and that they ſhould have been very happy, if they had been in the Religion. And the ſame ought to be done in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to thoſe Sons that aſpire to Marriage.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. We ought to converſe familiarly with their Daughters, entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them in our Colleges, when we conceive they will enter our Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, leading them to our Gardens to walk, and to our Country-Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, in which the Vacations are kept.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. Repreſent to them the pleaſant Contentment that they ſhall find here, and the Honour that Princes of divers Kingdoms give us. In ſhort, we ought to do all we can to gain the Youth, conducting them to the <hi>Refectory</hi> and Chambers, ſhewing them the Neatneſs, and delightful Converſation that is amongſt us, and the eaſineſs of obſerving our Rule, to which is promiſed the Glory of the Bleſſed.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. And alſo the Faculties we have, and Powers, not only in Temporal but Spiritual things, the eloquent Diſcourſes which are made in our Colleges; and let not the pleaſant and delightful Spiritual Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which were given us in the Name of the Virgin, as it were by revelation, be omitted, which may ſpur them on to embrace our Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; repreſenting alſo to them, that it is an enormous Crime to reſiſt the Divine Vocation. Laſtly, we ought to admit them as Spectators of our Exerciſes, that thereby we may the more eaſily diſpoſe them to become of our Society.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. Let the Maſters which are to inſtruct the Children of theſe Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows be appointed by us, who ought perpetually to exhort them to be of our Society, with Promiſes that if they will enter the ſame, they ſhall be received <hi>gratis;</hi> but if they will not, then we ought to procure their Mothers from time to time to deny them what is neceſſary, and make them ſee the Incumbrances and Confuſions in which the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance of their Famiiy is plunged.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:54204:20"/>
                     <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>Of the means to augment the Revenue of our Colleges.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p n="1">1. LEt none of our Society be admitted to the fourth Vow, while he expects any Inheritance, except he hath a Brother in our Society, which is younger and ſtouter than he, or upon ſome other very advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious account. Above and before all other things, we ought to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour our own Greatneſs, by the direction of our Superiors, who are the only Judges in this Caſe, and who ſhould labour that the Church of God may be in the higheſt degree of ſplendor, <hi>ad majorem Dei gloriam.</hi> And to attain this, Confeſſors of Princes, and rich Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, ſhould never fail to remonſtrate to them, that ſeeing they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Spiritual things from us, it is moſt juſt that we ſhould receive Temporal from them, for the good of our Society.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. We ought never to let any opportunity of taking any thing ſlip us, and if any thing be promiſed us, and forgotten, we muſt put them in mind of it, though this importunity ſhould happen to diminiſh the favour they may have for us.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. We ought not to appoint any for Confeſſors to Princes, and other great Men, who are not of great ability, and very eloquent, this Charge being of great import; but if it happens that any do not diſcharge the ſame with convenient vigor, we ought to reprove them, as not being well affected to the general good of the Society, telling them that we will ſoon ſend others into their places, for we have underſtood with great regret, that ſome Perſons have died ſuddenly, who by the default of their Confeſſors left no Goods to our Churches of great value; which came to paſs only, becauſe we were not dexterous enough to poſſeſs our ſelves of them in their Life-times, and yet they would have beſtowed them on us without any difficulty; for the acquiring theſe things doth not depend ſo much upon the Time, as the Will of them that give them.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. We ought to viſit the Houſes of Noble and Rich Widows, of which ours ought to inform themſelves prudently and dexterouſly, to ſee whether they will not, according to the cuſtom of other Chriſtians, leave ſomething to our Churches, in order to the obtaining Remiſſion of their Sins, and of the Sins of their Kindred and Friends: And we ſhould do the like to Prelates, and their Pariſhioners, whom we ought eſpecially to render friendly to <hi>our Society,</hi> for thereby we may gain much</p>
                     <p n="5">5. The Confeſſors ought to examine every Penitent, what are their Names and Sirnames, what Kindred and Friends they have, what hopes they have of ſucceeding in any Inheritance, and how they intend to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:54204:21"/>
diſpoſe of what they have; what Brothers, Siſters, or Heirs they have; how old, of what degree, of what inclination, or diſpoſition, or edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation they are of? They ſhould perſnade them that all theſe Queſtions do tend much to the clearing of the State of their Conſcience. And if there be any hope of Profit afterward, then they ought to appoint them a weekly Confeſſion for their Penance, to the intent that what hath been omitted at one time, may be made up at another enquiry; and ſo collecting all the Confeſſions of the Penitent, communicate them to the Superior, and take good counſel what is to be done.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. The ſame which hath been preſcribed to be done in relation to Widows, ought to be done alſo in relation to rich and wealthy Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, who are married, and yet have no Children: to Maids, who are rich and well affected to us. That having once gotten an entry into their Eſtates, we may with the greater facility join them to our own Revenues. But we ought eſpecially to take care, that we do nothing with too much haſte, but ſlowly by little and little, with good conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. We ought to ſtudy to acquire the good will of every one according to their capacity, complying with their manners and inclinations. And our Provincial ought to ſend expert Men into all thoſe places, where there is any conſiderable number of ſuch rich and wealthy Perſons, to the end they may give their Superiors a true and faithful account of all; and whenever any of ours are in their ſavour, they ought to extol very much the greatneſs of their Benefits, and of their Merits, which the other Monks, who are poor and needy, ſeldom do.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. Let the <hi>Stewards</hi> of our College, get an exact knowledg of the Houſes, Gardens, Quarries of Stone, Vineyards, Mannors, and other Riches of every one, who lives near the place where they reſide, and if it be poſſible, what degree of affection they have for us.</p>
                     <p n="9">9. In the next plac, we ſhould diſcover every Mans Office, and the Revenue of it, their Profeſſions, the Articles of their Contracts, which they may ſurely do by Confeſſions, by Meetings and by Entertainments, or by our truſty Friends. And generally whenever any Confeſſor lights upon a wealthy Perſon, from whom he hath good hopes of profit, he is obliged forth with to give notice of it, and diſcover it at his return.</p>
                     <p n="10">10. They ſhould alſo inform themſelves exactly, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there be no hopes of obtaining <note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>It ſignifies Leaſes, Purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes;</hi> &amp;c.</note> Bargains, Goods, Poſſeſſions, pious Gifts, and the like, in exchange for the admiſſion of their Sons into our Society.</p>
                     <p n="11">11. We ought to endeavour to know, if any Perſon well affected to us, intends any thing to our College, and whether he may be brought to purchaſe on this Condition, that after a certain time we ſhould have
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:54204:21"/>
ſuch Rents or Purchaſes <hi>Gratis;</hi> or whether our Society may expect a greater benefit from him, and how we may come by the ſame.</p>
                     <p n="12">12. We ought to let every one know the great need we have, the debts which oppreſs us, and the great expences we are forced to make.</p>
                     <p n="13">13. If our Society ſells any thing to our <hi>Devotes,</hi> Men or Women, it ought to be only upon this condition, that within a certain time it ſhall return <hi>gratis</hi> to us, and be reunited to our Revenues.</p>
                     <p n="14">14. If the rich Widows or married People, who are well affected to us, have Daughters only, we ought to perſuade them with great art to cauſe them to enter into the Religion; leaving them a ſmall Portion for that end, and ſo we may gain the remainder of their Eſtate; as Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey-Houſes, Mannors, and other Poſſeſſions. And ſo likewiſe, on the part of their Sons, to put them on with great care to imbrace our Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety; to fright them, and make them obedient to their Parents, teaching them to deſpiſe all low things, and making them know they are more obliged to follow Jeſus Chriſt, than their Parents, if they will have a due care of their Souls, for this will be to offer a kind of Sacrifice to our Society; to perſuade the laſt Heir of a Family, to enter it without the knowledg of his Parents, who ſhould be ſent to make his <hi>Nouiciate</hi> in a place of ſome diſtance, our General being firſt advertiſed of it.</p>
                     <p n="15">15. If there be a rich Widow our Friend, who hath Sons and Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and there be no hope of getting the Daughters into a Monaſtery, nor the Sons into our Society; the Superior ſhould ever lay the blame upon the Confeſſor, and therefore he ought to change him and put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother in his place, who may manage the Plot better; and if yet it ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed not, then he ought to perſuade their Mother to leave them ſome ſmall Penſion, and then ſelling what came by her and her Joynture, raiſe a conſiderable ſum of Money; and then try if we can induce her to give the whole to our Society, that ſhe may obtain pardon and expia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of her Sins, and her Husbands.</p>
                     <p n="16">16. If a Widow hath married a Widower, and hath by him Daughters or Sons, or only one Son, with Siſters by a former Husband, let firſt the younger Children be ſent to a Monaſtery, and then the elder, that we may the eaſier get their Pſtate.</p>
                     <p n="17">17. If any Widows, very much affected to our Society, and careful of their Salvation, having no Heirs, poſſeſs two or three Manors or other Inheritances, we ought to perſuade them to leave their Eſtates to our Colleges, and perſuade them to receive ſome ſmall annual Penſions from us, that they may ſerve God with the greater freedom, being releaſed from the troubles of the World, and ſo by degrees bring them from an annual Penſion to live as we do, that under pretence of Mortification and voluntary Poverty, they be as it were our Domeſticks, being as it
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:54204:22"/>
were reſigned up to our Wills. And for fear by the direction their kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred they ſhould be brought to recal their Bounty, it is fit to ſend them to ſpend the reſt of their Lives in ſome diſtant place, and in the interim tell them, this ſort of Life is an imitation of that of the <hi>Hermites,</hi> which is the moſt devout and humble ſort of Life that is.</p>
                     <p n="18">18. That our devout Perſons may think us poor, our Superiour ought to borrow Money upon promiſes entred before <hi>Notaries;</hi> it may be that upon their Death-Beds they may order the Notaries to put the ſaid ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations into our hands, for the Salvation of their Souls; for it is more eaſy to give in our Bonds, then to give us a conſiderable ſum of Money.</p>
                     <p n="19">19. It is fit to borrow a conſiderable ſum of Money on Mortgage, and then perſuade them to aſſign the Intereſt to ſome other College; that ſo one Revenue may increaſe another: and ſo in their laſt ſickneſs in compaſſion to our Poverty, if they do not give us the entire ſum, yet at leaſt they may be brought to aſſign a good part of it, for the building of ſome new College.</p>
                     <p n="20">20. We ſhould procure the friendſhip of ſome excellent Phyſician, that we may be called to viſit the Sick, and aſſiſt at the Paſſage of thoſe whom he ſerves.</p>
                     <p n="21">21. The Confeſſors ought not to be negligent in viſiting the Sick, eſpecially thoſe that diſpair, repreſenting to them the pains of Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Hell, telling them they cannot be ſaved without Charity; for thoſe who before were Covetous, uſe then to be moſt liberal to us, and it may be will preſently give all they have into our hands, which ours ſhould ſolicit all that ever they are able, for fear this favourable oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity ſlip them. And if a Woman in her Confeſſions accuſe the vices and ill uſages of her Husband towards her, of being the cauſe of her not ſubmitting to our Diſcipline, and that ſhe is much our Friend, we ought then to tell her ſhe cannot do God a more acceptable Service than to give us a good Sum of Money without her Husbands knowledg, for the relief of our neceſſities; that this is the beſt way to live for the future, in repoſe, and obtain Pardon both of her own and her Husband's Sins; for we have often known that by this means the ill Nature of Husbands have been changed into better Conditions.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. X. <hi>Of the Rigor and Diſcipline of our Society.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>SUperiours ſhould teſſifie that the Severity of this Diſcipline is ſuch, that beſides the reſerved Caſes, whoſoever of our Society, of what Age or Condition ſoever he be, ſhall divert any of our <hi>Devotes,</hi> or
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:54204:22"/>
Friends, from doing us good, perſuading them to embrace any other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion but ours, and who in any intended Reſignation of their Eſtates to our uſe, ſhall have expreſt any Tenderneſs, or Coldneſs, or ſhall ſolicite them to aſſign them to any other Order, or put them upon the beſtowing them upon their poor Kindred, or others; that all theſe ſhall be eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Mortal Enemies of our Society. And ſhall not be taken ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into favour again, but for ſometime at leaſt to be forbidden to hear Confeſſions, and be Mortified by low and abject Imployments, forcing them to teach the loweſt Forms, denying them degrees in Divinity. And that being ſeparated from the reſt at Dinner, it is neceſſary to inſult over them, chaſing them from all Recreations, Walks, and the more pleaſant Entertainments, taking out of their Chambers all Conveniencies, and often impoſing upon them public Penances; and after this, it will not be difficult to caſt them out of the Society. And if it happen that they complain of it to the Provincial, he ought not lightly to believe them, but ſhould excuſe what is done, by ſaying, They ought to obey their Superiours, in whatſoever is not ſinful. Nor need the Superiours be in the leaſt ſcrupulous to caſt theſe ſort of Men out of the Society. For our Order being conſtituted in a Society, no Man ought to wonder it hath the power of Expulſion: for it is eaſie to break the band of a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety; which are not obliging for ever. This right of Expelling, is as old as the Society it ſelf: Which appears evidently from hence, that the Society hath only Vows for the Maſters and Brothers, which have no Reciprocal Obligation, and the Society is not bound to entertain for ever thoſe that have made them; and therefore this Obligation binds only them that have made theſe Vows; and not the Society, which may at pleaſure caſt off thoſe that have made theſe Vows, and although ſome of the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety make four ſolemn Vows, and others but three, as in other Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, yet may theſe too be Expelled.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. XI. <hi>After what manner thoſe of the Society ſhould demean them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves towards thoſe that are Expell'd.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>IN as much as thoſe that are Expell'd out of our Society, may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicial to us, ſee how we ought to behave our ſelves towards them. And firſt, before any Man is Expell'd, we ſhould write to both the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral and Spiritual Lords, with whom he may happen to be in Credit, and to whom he may make his Retreat; telling them his ill Inclinations. his Vices and Defaults, according to that connizance he ſhall have give, of them to his Superioars, in diſcovering the ſecrets of his Conſcience.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:54204:23"/>
Upon which alſo they ſhall regulate the Conduct which ſhall be obſerved on his account in the Society, when ſhe renounces her right in him. If theſe Lords be well affected to us, then we ought to aggravate the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons we had to Expel him. We ſhould publiſh in our Exhortations, that he ſeeks very ardently to be receiv'd again into our Company, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marking as the cauſes of his Expulſion, thoſe things for which the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple hates us moſt; and ſo we may Expel whom we will, with great ſhew of Reaſon. If he that is Expell'd meets any belief amongſt thoſe he diſcourſeth with againſt us, this muſt be remedied by the means of the moſt conſiderable of the Fathers of our Society, who ſhall oppoſe, to what he may ſay, the holineſs of our Society, and the great good it hath done in the Church of God, the reputation of our good Lives, and the ſound Doctrine we teach, and that for theſe Excellencies we have the advantage to attend Kings and Princes; and the great Men chuſe out of our Body, their Confeſſors and Preachers: they ſhall inlarge much up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our Zeal for the ſalvation of Men in general, and eſpecially of thoſe of our own Society. Let thoſe be invited to entertainments with us, who may give the Expell'd perſon any protection, and let them be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded that they ought not to give him the leaſt ſupport, and that they ought to have favourable opinions of the Order; and then tell them the Reaſons why he was Expell'd, ordering the matter ſo, as they may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear plauſible, and telling them exactly his Faults, without omitting any one, although we have not the leaſt certainty of them. And we ought alſo to be very careful not to procure any Benefice for thoſe we have once Expell'd, if they do not firſt give a good ſum of Money to the Society; or if they have not made it their Heir, or if they do not in ſome other extraordinary manner teſtifie their undertaking our Intereſt. And let the Confeſſors perſuade Kings and Princes, who are the Patrons to them, the ſame things, and let them take their opportunities from their liberality, and from the affection they bear to our Society to found ſome College, or do us ſome other ſuch like favour. If it happens that they which have been Expell'd out of our Society, have any Credit in the World, let it be acquainted with their Lives, their Manners, and their Faults, which may be ſpread abroad by the means of our Friends and <hi>Devotes:</hi> And to the end that they too may not favour in the leaſt thoſe which are Expell'd out of our Society, let them be affrighted with Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures; and if they ſtill perſiſt, let Abſolution be denied them. Let the good qualities of him that is Expell'd, be leſſened by ſubtile Diſcourſes, and full of Ambiguity, ſo as that all the belief Men have of him may be deſtroyed. And laſtly, Let the misfortunes of thoſe that have been Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell'd, be publiſh'd by way of Compaſſion, that others being warn'd by it, may be neceſſitated to continue in the Society againſt their wills.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="12" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:54204:23"/>
                     <head>CHAP. XII. <hi>Of the Choice of the Young-Men which are to be received into the Society, and of the manner.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THere is need of great Prudence, and of an extreme degree of Diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for the receiving of Young Men into the Society; they ought to be Beautiful, Noble, and Rich. And that they may be drawn to this, the Maſters of the ſeveral Forms, ought to treat them with great Goodneſs, they ought not to ſuffer their Regents to inſult over them; they ſhould oft commend them, they ſhould give them the Prize. They ſhould entertain and divert them ſometimes in our Country-Houſes. Sometimes they ſhould Chaſtiſe them with the reſt, objecting Crimes againſt them upon Conjectures, and uſing ſeverity and rigorous Reproof. They ſhould repreſent to them, that they ſhall be Damn'd eternally by the Bent Youth hath to all ſorts of Evils, if they enter not the Society. Yet they ſhould not be receiv'd ſo ſoon as they demand to be admitted into the Society; but be delay'd for ſome time, and in the interim be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain'd with the repreſentation of the ſweetneſs of our Rule; for by this means their deſires encreaſing, they will make the greater ſuit to be received: And if any of them who have made this demand, ſhall ſeem to deſire to go back, then ſhall be repreſented to him the Zeal, which he at firſt expreſt to get into the Society. But becauſe there is great difficulty in drawing in the Children of great Birth, and eſpecially the Children of them that are great in their Country, it is fit to ſend ſuch to make their Noviciat, or Trial at <hi>Rome,</hi> after having advertiſed the General, or Provincial of that Province. If it be in <hi>Germany, France,</hi> or <hi>Italy,</hi> that they will enter into our Society, they ſhall be received without any difficulty; and in any other place where we have the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of the Prince: For under ſuch a Protector, theſe and ſuch like things may be done; becauſe their Subjects having need of our favour, they will not eaſily riſe up againſt us, or if they do it, they will gain nothing by it. No opportunity ſhould be loſt for the drawing in thoſe Children, which come from other Provinces to ſtudy in our Colleges, eſpecially when their Money comes to fail by Gaming, for then out of meer ſhame of this loſs, and fear of their Parents ill uſage, they will ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer themſelves to be perſuaded. This hath excellent ſucceſs in <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>Poland,</hi> and to the end the Kindred and Friends of them who c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>me amongſt us, may be herewith contented, they ſhould be acquainted with the excellence of our Inſtitution, the great applauſe the World give us, &amp; the Honour Princes have done our Society: It is fit alſo to inſinuate
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:54204:24"/>
into their Friends, and diſpoſe them to be contented with it before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand, if their quality, and the advantage of our Affairs require it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="13" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. XIII. <hi>Of our Religious Women.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THe Confeſſors ought to take care they do not offend our Religious Women: for there have been many amongſt them which have done us much good, and contributed to the Founding of our Colleges, having given one half of their Fortunes to us, by the conſent of their Monaſtery and Abbeſs: And for this cauſe they ſhould not be diſqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eted about their incloſure, but leave this care to the Biſhops: They ſhould rather apply themſelves to preſerve their good will, for fear they ſhould diſturb us in the poſſeſſion of the one half of their Goods, which they have given us, by demanding them again.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="14" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. XIV. <hi>Of the reſerved Caſes, and of thoſe Cauſes for which a Man may be Expell'd out of the Society.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>BEſides the Caſes contain'd in this Inſtruction, from which the Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour only can Abſolve, or the ordinary Confeſſor by his permiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; which are Sodomy, Fornication, Adultery, Whoredom, unchaſt Touches, and the Machinations of any Perſon for any Cauſe whatever againſt the Society; it is fit to know, that there are other cauſes for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelling a guilty Perſon out of the Society, and that they ought not to abſolve them till they have promiſed at the Tribunal of Confeſſion, that they will declare thoſe Offences to their Superior, either by themſelves, or by their Confeſſor. And if it appear that the Sin was acted with another, and that a great Prejudice may thereby happen to the Society, then no Abſolution ought to be given to the Penitent, if he doth not promiſe to write of it to the General himſelf, or conſent that the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor or Superior ſhall write to him about it, and without this the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent ſhall not be abſolved. And when the General ſhall have known the Crime, he ſhall confer with the Secretary, and appoint the Penance, which the Penitent ſhall undergo, which if he ſhall not ſubmit to, he can never be lawfully abſolved. The Confeſſor ſhould nevertheleſs for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear ſaying, that the Penitent ought to be expelled out of the Society for this cauſe. If the Penitent declare it freely out of Confeſſion, then he may be expelled; but if he will not ſo tell it, then the ſame Courſe
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:54204:24"/>
ought to be obſerved with him, which is obſerved by the Rule againſt thoſe that are convicted; and in the interim he ſhall not be abſolved till he will declare his Crime publickly. If any Confeſſor ſhall learn that any Perſon, who is not of the Society, ſhall have committed any diſhoneſt Action with any of our Religious Perſons, then he or the ſhall be refuſed Abſolution, of what Sex ſoever that Perſon be, till that Perſon hath out of Confeſſion revealed the Party; and if this be done, the Penitent ſhall be abſolved, and the guilty Party expell'd out of the Society. If two of our Religious Perſons commit the Crime of Sodomy together, he that will not confeſs it, ſhall be expelled, and he that firſt confeſſeth it, ſhall be retained, but ſo ill treated, that he ſhall be forced to forſake us. The So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety being a Body, it may for that cauſe diſcharge it ſelf of ſuch Perſons, as ſhall in proceſs of time, appear dull in their Manners or Diſcourſes. The Superiors alſo may for any cauſe whatever expell all ſorts of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, after they have advertiſed the General; and to oblige them to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part the more quickly, they ſhall be ill treated, and every thing done con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to their Inclination; they ſhall be refuſed what ever they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, tho it be of no conſequence; they ſhall be hindred from ſtudying Divinity, and be ſubjected to ſuch Superiors as they love not; none ſhall remain in the Society, who diſobey their Superiors, who complain of them in the preſence of others, or expreſs their diſlike of the Conduct of the Society in relation to Widows, and the management of their Eſtates, and who commend the <hi>Venetians</hi> who have driven away the Society. A little before the expelling any Perſon, let him be rudely abuſed, and taken from all regular Emploiments, and put ſometimes upon one thing, and ſometimes upon another; and in the interim let him be reproached with the having ill diſcharged his Truſt, and let the worſt Penances be impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for the ſmalleſt Faults. During the time of Repaſt, let his Faults be publiſhed by the Reader, till he be overwhelmed with ſhame; and if then any impatience appear in him, let him be expelled, as one that ſcandali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeth the reſt who are preſent, and rally on him. But then in the firſt place let a review of what he hath, be taken, and let him be ſent into ſome Country-houſe, or near College, and ſo let him be ſent thence to the place where he leaſt expects.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="15" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. XV. <hi>Which of the Society ought to be kept in, and managed.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>FIrſt of all, the excellent Workmen, who contribute not only to the Spiritual but Temporal Good of the Society, as the Confeſſors of rich Widows, which yet ſhould be taken from them, when they begin
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:54204:25"/>
to be oppreſſed with old Age, that others more youthful and vigorous may be ſent in their ſtead. And to theſe whatever they demand for their Diet and Cloathing, and other things, ought to be granted, neither ought the Miniſters of Penance to diſquiet them. The Superiors ſhall not lightly believe that which is reported of them. It is neceſſary alſo to have ſome Conſideration for them who acquaint the Superiors with the ſmalleſt faults they can obſerve in others; and alſo for them who according to their places know how to mortify others, not out of Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but Zeal for the Religious Diſcipline. Yet ſweetneſs ſhould be uſed towards thoſe younger Perſons, whoſe Kindred are our Benefactors and Founders; and upon this account they ſhould be ſent to ſtudy at <hi>Rome,</hi> or if they perform their Studies in the Provinces, all things that may gain their Affections, ſhould be granted to them. It is fit alſo to treat fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourably all thoſe young Religious Perſons, who have not yet given their Eſtates to the Society; but when they have once done this, it is fit to feed them with Bread, and not with Milk. It is fit alſo to have reſpect to thoſe who diſpoſe Children of Quality to enter our Society, as to Perſons well affected to it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="16" type="chapter">
                     <head>CHAP. XVI. <hi>Of what is to be avoided or obſerved beſides all this.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>FOr fear we ſhould be accuſed of being too covetous of Riches, it is fit to refuſe ſmall Alms, for the ordinary Services which thoſe of our Society perform. No lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e ſhould be given to Perſons of mean condition to bury in our Churches. Thoſe Widows ſhould be treated ſeverely, who have impoveriſhed themſelves by their bounty to us; and the ſame Courſe ſhould be taken with thoſe of our Order, who have given their Eſtates to the Society. They may ſometimes be expell'd too, either without allowing them any thing at all, or but a very little, under pretence of the Charges the Society have expended about them.</p>
                     <p>Let the Superiors keep theſe ſecret Advices with great care, and let them not be communicated but to a very few diſcreet Perſons, and that only by parts: and let them inſtruct others with them, when they have profitably ſerved the Society; and then let them not communicate them as Rules they received, but as the Effects of their own prudence. But if they ſhould happen to fall into the hands of Strangers, who ſhould give them an ill ſence and conſtruction; let them be aſſured the Society owns them not in that ſence, which ſhall be confirmed by inſtancing in thoſe of our Order who aſſuredly know them not.</p>
                     <p>Let alſo the general Advices, and printed or written Conſtitutions of our <hi>Society,</hi> be oppoſed againſt them.</p>
                     <p>Laſtly, let Information be given, whether any of our own Members have communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated them (for no <hi>Superior</hi> ought to be <hi>negligent in the keeping ſuch conſiderable Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of the Society).</hi> And if there be the leaſt ſuſpicion of any Perſon, let it be charged upon him, and let him be espell'd out of the <hi>Society.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
